<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A friendlie communcication or dialogue betweene Paule and Damas wherein is disputed how we are to vse the pleasures of this life. By Samuel Byrd, Master of Art, and fellow not long since of Benet Colledge.</title>
            <author>Bird, Samuel, d. 1604.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1580</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 199 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 93 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16163</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3086</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102321</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838110</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838110</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2469</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16163)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2469)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 280:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A friendlie communcication or dialogue betweene Paule and Damas wherein is disputed how we are to vse the pleasures of this life. By Samuel Byrd, Master of Art, and fellow not long since of Benet Colledge.</title>
                  <author>Bird, Samuel, d. 1604.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 80 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By T. East] for Iohn Harrison the younger, dwelling in Pater noster Roe, at the signe of the Anker, and are there to be solde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1580.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1900.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2469:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2469:1"/>
            <p>A friendlie communication or Dialogue betweene Paule and Demas.</p>
            <p>wherein is diſputed <hi>how we are to vſe the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of this life. By</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel Byrd, Maſter of <hi>Art, and fellow not long ſince of Benet Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>DM <hi>Imprinted at London</hi> for Iohn Hariſon the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, dwelling in Pater no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Roe, at the ſigne of the Anker, and are <hi>there to be ſolde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1580.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2469:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2469:2"/>
            <head>¶ TO THE CHRISTIAN Reader, Samuel Byrd wiſheth grace, mercie, and peace, from God the <hi>Father, and from our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T maie (perhaps) ſeeme ſomewhat ſtraunge, there bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo manie lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and godlie bookes ſet out, that I haue not bene diſcouraged thereby from writing: I deſire therfore leaue of the good Reader, that I maie bee heard what I can ſaie for my ſelfe. Firſt therefore it maie be anſwered, that though a matter be handled of neuer ſo manie: yet the varietie of time and place, maie alwaies mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſome new and profitable matter to ſpeake of. Beſide this, I haue ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall reaſons, and thoſe alſo manie, to alledge for my ſelfe in this behalfe. Firſt, it may be ſaid, that though the Argument heere handled, eſpecially dice and card plaie, haue bene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, as it were by a general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of all Nations: yet are there verie fewe founde which haue in
<pb facs="tcp:2469:3"/> particulars vnfolded, &amp; laide abrode the vglineſſe thereof. They haue taken the beaſtlineſſe of this game to be ſo plaine, and ſo euident a caſe, that they haue not vſed manie rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the proofe thereof. And leaſt I ſhould ſeeme to affirme this thing at a venture, without ſome triall, onelie to excuſe my ſelfe: the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſhall vnderſtand, that I haue made inquirie, &amp; that the moſt that hath bene ſaid of anie that I can heare of, is of Paſcaſius, which hath entered into the ſecrets of this idle paſtime, &amp; hath bewraied the hid thoughts of gameſters, and their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempered affections. In this reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect (I ſaie) he hath ſaid very much, although concerning the vnlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this game, hee hath ſaid nothing at all. Daneus, a learned di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, hath proued that this game is vnlawfull, but yet in fewer wordes then can ſatiſfie the patrones ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. I haue not heard of manie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and I am the ſooner brought to thinke, that but few haue taken
<pb facs="tcp:2469:3"/> paines in this thing, becauſe the forenamed Paſcaſius, making great inquirie, could not heare of anie (as he ſaith) that hath of purpoſe writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten a treatiſe of this matter. It ought therefore (as I ſaid before) the leſſe to be accounted an vnne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie worke, which ſpeaketh of that, that ſo few haue ſpoken of, eſpeciallie in our Engliſh tongue. And I haue ben the bolder to take this thing vppon mee, becauſe I cannot thinke, but that the Lord, which cannot awaie with idlneſſe, and hath graunted me ſo great lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, requireth it at my handes. This my enterpriſe ſhall the leſſe bee meruailed at, if men conſider that my miſerable experience in theſe vnthriftie games, canne make mee ſpeake that, which thoſe that want the like experience cannot, though otherwiſe they bee neuer ſo eloquent. Beſide that, it ſhall make more for the glorie of God, and more againſt this ſinne, when it is cried out vppon, of him that
<pb facs="tcp:2469:4"/> hath had his delight therein, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then when it is ſpoken againſt of him that hath had no acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce with it: and hee teacheth well, which would haue vs, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerpere ex ipſis malis, quod in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt boni. I ſhall alſo, by this meanes, cheere and make glad, the heartes of thoſe good men, whome I doubt not but I haue heeretofore gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and vexed with following this confuſed and fooliſh gaming. Neither ſhall it be a ſmall comfort vnto mine owne ſoule, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie for the preſent time, but euen when thoſe that ſtand about my bedde can doe mee no good, when the women are almoſt readie to binde vp my face in a napkin: It will bee (I ſaie) at that time a great ſtaie vnto my ſoule, when I ſhall conſider that, that hande, that hath beene ſo defiled with the curſed bones, and with ſuch filthie papers, now hath beene at defiaunce with them, and hath
<pb facs="tcp:2469:4"/> writ againſt them. This I doubt not in my greateſt extremitie, will bee a witneſſe vnto me, that both hand and foote, and euerie part of mee are purged, and clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and purefied with the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bloudſhedding of the ſonne of God my almightie redeemer. All theſe reaſons beeing well waied of mine indifferent Reader, this my booke ſhall (I hope) haue the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter enterteinement at his handes. Concerning the matter and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce of this treatiſe, my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe was, to ſette downe a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene the childe of God, and a naturall man, in vſing the preſent thinges of this life. The naturall man, as a brute beaſt; look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vpon whatſoeuer is before him, and neuer goeth further, and as a brutiſh ſwine, which feedeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an Acorne tree, mindeth one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie the Acornes that lie ſeattered vppon the ground, neuer looking vp to the tree from whence they came: ſo this people nuſſel themſelues
<pb facs="tcp:2469:5"/> in the creatures, neuer lifting vp their heart vnto the Creator: and ſome are ſo groſe, that they thinke God is greatlie honoured, when they are ſo much delighted with the creature, that they are neuer ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfied therewith. For when their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ares are altogether buſied in pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and ſinging, when they reſt their ſoules, &amp; laie themſelues down in the melodie of Organs and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering, they call it an heauenlie noiſe: but it is an earthlie noiſe, &amp; they are Epicures that delight ſo much in it. And therefore Plautus, deſcribing Epicures, ſetteth them out by theſe words: Viuunt muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cè. For whie maie not the dronken glutton as well ſaie, that ſweete luſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious meate and drinke, haue an heauenlie taſt? Manie of theſe men can tell the naturall reaſon of earthquakes, windes, ſnowe, haile, and raine, and of all meteors: they can ſhewe reaſons, howe meate and drinke doth nouriſh our life: but the Lord and giuer of life, they will
<pb facs="tcp:2469:5"/> not acknowledge. They are buſied altogether in ſecondarie meanes, but the cauſe of all cauſes, the high and mightie God that holdeth the ſterne both of ſea &amp; land, &amp; ruleth with his becke both heauen &amp; earth, &amp; work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vſuallie by meanes, oftentimes without meanes, ſometimes contrarie to all meanes, they wil not remember. If a man ſpeak of this firſt cauſe, they thinke there is no wit in anie ſuch talke: they are alwaies in their A, B, C, as Caluin that good man noteth: &amp; as blinde buzzards keepe altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther below: but the learned Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, like an eagle mounteth vp aloft, &amp; vſeth the creatures as ſteppes and ſtaires to aſcend vnto the high God, he is the reſting place of their ioie, he is the ſtay &amp; center of all their delights. They pitie the fooliſhnes of ſuch, as make their back &amp; their bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, their bowling, dicing &amp; carding their God. For how can the vanitie of theſe vaine things helpe them in the time of need? When they are ſore ſick, their gaie coats muſt be let off.
<pb facs="tcp:2469:6"/> When their ſtomacks be taken from them, what good will their meate &amp; drinke do them? They cannot ſtand to bowle, they cannot ſit vp to play a ſet at Maw. If they thinke that the ſight of their companions will eaſe their grief, they cannot haue that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for their delight is in pleaſant things, but the ſight of a ſicke man is altogether vnpleaſant. They will not be tender hearted, they will not be like affected, they will not weepe with him that weepeth, they wil not by ſorrowing by thee, beare parte of thy griefe. Then ſhall thy ſoule be heauie, &amp; thou ſhalt haue none to comfort thee, but ſhalt die in thy ſinnes. This ſhall the end of theſe men be, for they ſhall eate the fruite of their owne labour. When theſe things come vppon them, then ſhall they know that they had good counſell giuen them. But I forgette my ſelfe, which reaſon with the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie &amp; the back, which haue no eares to heare. I may wiſh well, &amp; ſo foorth, but there is little hope of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendement,
<pb facs="tcp:2469:6"/> I will turne my ſpeach therfore to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that maie do good in this matter, &amp; haue authoritie to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh &amp; put down this ſin. And I hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie beſeech all thoſe that are put in truſt with any ſuch office vnder her Maieſtie, that they would in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe diſcharge that dutie that is laid vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in baniſhing this iniquitie that hath ſuch a great traine of ſin to wait vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it. A man (ſaith our ſtatute) that ſuffereth for his gaine vnlawfull games in his houſe, ſhall forfet, for euery day. 40. s. except he hath a pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>card: &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſhall be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teined in the ſame placard, what game ſhalbe vſed in the ſame houſe, &amp; what perſons, ſhall play thereat: to this he muſt be bound in the Chaunſerie, before he put it in execution. The gameſters themſelues ſhall forfette for euery time vi. s. eight pence, but if they be ſeruing men &amp; men of occupation (vnles it be in Chriſtmas) they ſhall forfet for euery time 20. s. And both ſeruing men and other beſide this forfet, may be caſt in priſon, vntill
<pb facs="tcp:2469:7"/> they be bound in a ſufficient ſumme to play no more. The officers that make not ſerch euery week, or at the leaſt euery moneth, where it is like vnlawfull games are vſed, ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fet 40. s. And to the end that both magiſtrates, &amp; others, might the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be put in mind of their dutie in this behalfe, proclamation of this ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute muſt be made euery quarter, in euery market. If I ſhould ſet downe how far the officers are from execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this good law, they might be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, &amp; hang downe their heads. For what a ſhamefull thing is it, that they ſhould not only not put downe this ſinne: but put to their helping hand to ſet it vp. They are bound to ſearch wher it is likelie ſuch vnlawfull games are vſed: but they giue lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe to thoſe men to vit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle whom they know, that they will keepe all kinde of ill rule, &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine lawles paſtimes. What can be more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie to their dutie that they are bound and ſworne vnto? They<note place="margin">2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. 10. 27.</note> ſhould knock downe their ſignes, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:2469:7"/> make a iakes of their houſes, or a draught houſe to feed ſwine in: but they make them ſanctuaries for ſin. Thoſe dronken beaſts, to whom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was ſome paine to ſeeke vp their copeſmates, now they haue more libertie to riot themſelues, &amp; to call gameſters vnto them. If all the dronken beaſts in the town had laid their heads together, what other thing would they haue deſired? Of themſelues they could not haue brought this thing to paſſe, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Magiſtrate muſt help them. O that men would conſider aright of this thing. We all know, that when but one priuate man doth commit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny truſt to the faithfulneſſe of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, what trecherie is it, one to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the other? For the one had not bene hurt, except he had commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his truſt vnto the other. He ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped he wold haue ben an aid to him. To whoſe faithfulneſſe ſhall he then flie, ſeing he is hurt by him to whom he hath committed himſelfe? A man may be defended againſt another, for
<pb facs="tcp:2469:8"/> he putteth no truſt in him: but to take heede of him, whom without breach of loue he could not once ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, it is almoſt vnpoſſible. Seeing therefore it is ſo hainous a matter, for one priuate man to be vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to another, how great treacherie &amp; treaſon ſhall we thinke it is, to be put in truſt of ſuch honourable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages, in ſo waightie a matter, as concerneth not onely the ſafetie of one man, but of an whole countrey, not onely to neglect this charge, but to betray the truth, &amp; to ſtrengthen the enemie againſt it? Beare with me (good Reader) though I be earneſt in this matter: for this couſoning ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, that I ſpeake againſt, is the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that begetteth, the mother that bringeth foorth, and the nourſe that bringeth vp, all kinde of ſinne what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer. And who can remedie this thing, but ſuch as haue authoritie, &amp; are put in truſt with this matter? The cauſe of this loſenes is, becauſe men would faine be accounted piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. If a gameſter be of any wealth,
<pb facs="tcp:2469:8"/> then he plaies away nothing but his owne; though poore men looſe their cuſtomers, &amp; be vndone with bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them companie. If they be all poore that play, then it is pittie to trouble them. The ſcripture indeed doth oftentimes commend the poore vnto the Magiſtrates, they muſt nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther oppreſſe them themſelues in their priuate affaires, neither muſt they ſuffer others to doe them vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence: but when poore men do iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie vnto the poore, when in ſteed of following their calling, they follow dronkennes, and idle gaming, neuer regarding whether their poore wife &amp; children ſinke or ſwim: when by this means beſides other miſchiefes, in a ſhort time the whole pariſh muſt be charged with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; their charge, who ſeeth not that in this caſe to pity them, &amp; to let them goe vnpuniſhed, is extreame crueltie? The mercifull God, notwithſtanding he ſetteth down a ſpecial charge for the poore: yet when they are thus vnrulie, he ſtraitly commandeth the Magiſtrate
<pb facs="tcp:2469:9"/> to haue no reſpect of perſon: Thou ſhalt not (ſaith he) fauour the perſon of the poore. Leui. 19. And againe, Thou ſhalt not eſteeme a poore man in his cauſe. Exo. 23. He repeateth his ſaieng for feare of forgetting.</p>
            <p>Euery man is euen a beaſt in his owne vnderſtanding. We know not what it is to be cruell, &amp; what it is to be mercifull, &amp; therefore we muſt lerne of the only wiſe God, ſeing he vouchſafeth to teach vs. Puniſh him, puniſh him: ſeemes to be a cruell ſpeach in their cares: but they heare not the pitiful co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint of the poore children that call for bread &amp; drink, &amp; thorough the noting of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, there is none to giue them. If the puniſhment that is laid vppon a poore wicked man for his amende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſeeme cruell, which would alſo fraie thoſe that ſee his puniſhment, or heard of it, from committing the like fault: what great crueltie ſhall we think it to be, to grieue the harts of all righteous Lots, that can not chuſe but mourne, when they ſee ſin
<pb facs="tcp:2469:9"/> vnpuniſhed? What crueltie is it to ſe women &amp; children almoſt ſtarued, &amp; the whole countrie grow into de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caie? The mercifull God open the eies of our Magiſtrates, &amp; make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſee a difference betweene mercifull ſeueritie &amp; cruell pitie. We haue an Engliſh prouerbe, which ſaith, that fooliſh pittie marreth a citie: but it is little thought vppon. They maie perhappes thinke they ſhall bee well thought of, by ſuffering the wicked to go ſcotfree, but it can not be. The people ſhal curſe ſuch a one, &amp; the multiude ſhall abhorre him: but to them that rebuke the wicked ſhalll be ſweeteneſſe, &amp; vpon them ſhal come the bleſsing of euery good man. Pro. 24. 23. For open rebuke is better then ſecret loue. And though the parties puniſhed, winch a little at the firſt: yet hee that reproueth a man, ſhall finde more fauour at the laſt, then he that flattereth with his tongue. If men wold but open their eies, experience would teach them the truth of that which I ſay. For,
<pb facs="tcp:2469:10"/> by reaſon of their fearefulneſſe and looſeneſſe, this waies men make no account of them: they deſpiſe the Lord, &amp; therfore the Lord deſpiſeth them. Now they do nothing, they are accounted as a king in a ſtage play, that only maketh a ſhow, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath done, he goeth his waies: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as otherwiſe the Lord would cauſe men to loue &amp; honor them. To keep their court dinners, or to haue their men &amp; officers to waite vpon them, is but an outward thing, &amp; an acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie matter to giue ſome counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce to their office: but the chiefe thing, the eſſentiall part of their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is, to doe iuſtice &amp; iudgement. But men are hard to be intreated in this matter. I therefore, beſeech all paſtors &amp; teachers, that they would not ſuffer themſelues to be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued witht he diſguiſed names of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or viccar, which names the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture knoweth not: but that they would remember, that they are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed as continuall watch men to ring the alarum bell, &amp; to beat &amp; to
<pb facs="tcp:2469:10"/> knocke at the conſciences of men, eſpecially of the Magiſtrates, which maie do all in all in this matter. For, it is great pittie, that they ſhuld wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſo great a benefit, as is the putting them in minde of their dutie, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſeing the whole Church recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth ſo great loſſe by their ſlacke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. If I ſpake of mine owne head, my words might be little ſet by: for who am I that any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld eſteme of my ſaying? But becauſe they be the words of the great God, they muſt be ſet by. Apollos was a very eloquent learned man, &amp; yet he was very well content to be more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed of a poore ſimple man: I deſire my Reader, that he would do the like. For I proteſt before the Lord, &amp; his Angells, &amp; before all the world, that I haue not ſpoken anie thing for any delight that I haue in reprouing: the truth whereof, the Reader may eaſily ſee, if he conſider that I haue reprooued no mans fault ſo much as mine owne. If I ſeeme to be more vehement then needeth,
<pb facs="tcp:2469:11"/> the cauſe thereof is, becauſe it is both long, ſince this our good ſtatute was made, &amp; alſo a contrary cuſtome hath almoſt ouergrowne it. It hath bene ſmoothered &amp; ſhamefully kept vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of a long time. And it is noted of one, that a Law, the farder it is from the firſt authoritie, which is as it were the firſt ſtroke wherewith it is firſt ſent abroad, the weaker it is. And that a cuſtome, the longer it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth, the ſtronger it is. I ſpeak not this, to end any ſhould be diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from labouring againſt this ſin, (for the word of God is mightie to bring down eueryſtrong hold, &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery high thought, that lifteth vp it ſelfe againſt the almightie: but that we ſhold rouſe vp our ſelues to fight more manfullie againſt it, ſeeing it hath ſo manie, &amp; ſo mightie enemies to defende it. And becauſe there is little hope, that the Lord will take awaie this loſeneſſe of life from vs, either by preaching or by the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and diligence of the godlie ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, ſo long as we caſt away from
<pb facs="tcp:2469:11"/> vs ſo churliſhlie his bleſſed diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, that hath bene ſo louingly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered: let vs throw our ſelues downe and craue forgiueneſſe for this our great rebellion, &amp; giue enterteinme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to it at the laſt, that the vſe &amp; praiſe of our catholike religion maie bee ſeene, and that it maie appeare in hir perfect beautie. We ſee nowe, that euerie bodie maie do what him liſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, without controlement. The Church maie ſeeme to bee nothing els, but a companie of outlawes. And what reproch is this to the holy and righteous Lord Ieſus Chriſt, which is the Lord thereof? What Chriſtian heart doth not bleed, to ſee open &amp; common dronkards to come to the Church, and to be accounted catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes? How wonderfullie doth this ſinne preuaile for want of church diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline? Know you not (ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) that a leauen ſowreth a whole lumpe of dowe? How manie are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, whileſt the corrupted parties are not cut off? What great commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie is the whole Church depriued
<pb facs="tcp:2469:12"/> off, for want of this communication? If theſe filthie perſons were thus ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed the Church, &amp; deliuered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Sathan, vntill they had acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged their fault, and waſhed their faces with teares of repentance before all the congregation, this fearfull pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment would make others afraid to offend. The parties that hath of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended ſhall receiue a ſinguler com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie by this thing: for now they be not of the Church, and yet are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted to be of the Church: they thinke their caſe is verie good, and harden themſelues in their ſins, and ſo goe to hell (as it were) in a ſleepe, before they be aware: wheras by this wholſome diſcipline they would be awakened out of their deepe ſleepe, they would be made aſhamed, and ſo repent. Thus if they were confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in this world, they ſhould bee glorified in the world to come: vpon their repentance they ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued againe, then ſhould they, not onely be in the Church, but of the Church: theyr ſinnes which were ſo
<pb facs="tcp:2469:12"/> faſt bound in heauen, but not in earth, ſhould then be looſed, both in heauen &amp; in earth. Theſe things are confeſſed &amp; wiſhed for in our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion booke, as it were by a generall conſent of the whole Realme, &amp; that manie yeares ago: &amp; yet we ſtand at a ſtaie, and account thoſe good men our enimies that perſwade vs to the practiſe of it. The Lord for his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ſake, that ſitteth in the heauens, and laugheth his enimies to ſcorne, &amp; that can bring to paſſe with the tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of an hand, whatſoeuer he wil, bring this thing to paſſe. Wherfore ſhall the Papiſts ſaie, We neuer ſaw the like wickedneſſe in our fathers daies? O Lord deliuer thy word from this reproch, and deliuer vs from the ſlauerie of ſin &amp; Sathan, &amp; our own rebellious practiſes, to freedome &amp; libertie, which is no where els to be found, but in putting on the eaſie yoke of Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; in being go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned by his word. We ſhal not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anie longer vſe the name of Chriſt, as men are wont to vſe an olde cloke,
<pb facs="tcp:2469:13"/> which put it on when any ſtormy te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſt is towards the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; are aſhamed of it when the ſtorme is ouer. Men ſhall not then anie longer vſe the calling vppon the name of God, as they vſe Aqua vitae, only when they lye a dieng: but they ſhall profeſſe the calling of his name throughout the whole courſe of their life: then ſhall not the ſon of God be aſhamed of vs before his father. If the glorious kingdome of Ieſus Chriſt were thus ſet vp, we ſhould haue euen an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vpon earth. I am afraide I haue troubled my Reader with loking an Epiſtle, and therefore I will heere take my leaue of him, wiſhing him well to fare in the Lord.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord, <hi>Samuel Byrd.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <head>The ſumme of euerie Chapter.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>VVhat pleaſures are lawfull, and that we maie offend, by vſing them too little, or too much. Chap. 1. fol.</hi> 1.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VVhat games are ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie vnlawfull. Cha. 2. fol.</hi> 12.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Continuing to much at lawfull games, maketh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                        <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                     </gap> Chap. 3. fol</hi> 29.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>That our kind of dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing is vtterlie vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Chap. 4. fol. 34. Of Dice and Cards. Chap. 5. fol.</hi> 37.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A remedy againſt ſuch euils, as haue ben be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpoken of. Chap. 6. fol.</hi> 70.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINI<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2469:13"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>A friendlie communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> or dio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>loge betweene Paule and Demas, wherein is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted how wee are to vſe the pleaſures of this life.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>The firſt Chapter.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DEmas.</speaker>
                  <p>I am come to ſée how you doe ſir, for me thinke it is long ſince I ſawe you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>It is long ſince I ſawe you in déede, but I will not ſaie you are therefore welcome, for if you would come oftener, you ſhould be much more welcome.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>De:</speaker>
                  <p>Well, bicauſe as you ſaie, I come ſo ſeldome, I will tarrie with you ſo much the longer, &amp; if it were not for hindering your ſtudie, you ſhould haue me dwell with you this whole after-noone, for I haue manie things to talke with you off, you ſhall ſée I will make you werie of me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I go. The laſt time we were in companie together, if you remember, there was much talke had to and fro,
<pb facs="tcp:2469:14"/> how we ſhould vſe this preſent world. And me thinke it was well ſaid of one, that ſéeing it is the will of God to haue vs liue in this world: It is likewiſe his pleſure to haue vs inioy the pleaſures of this life. And yet on the other ſide, the riotous life of a great manie was found fault withall, &amp; that alſo not without good cauſe. I would therefore gladlie learne ſome certeintie in this matter, I would gladly learne I ſaie, when we vſe the pleaſures of this world aright, and when we abuſe them. But to the end you might vnderſtand my meaning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, you ſhall vnderſtand that I call thoſe the pleaſures of this life, not which are ſimplie euill as adultrie is, or ſuch things as we inioie by ſtelth, but I ſpeake of ſuch as maie be both vſed, &amp; not vſed without anie breach of the commaundement: And bicauſe I am ſomwhat doubtfull what thoſe are that are of this kinde, I praie you tell me what they are, and how a man maie be bolde to vſe them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>The pleaſures of this life
<pb facs="tcp:2469:14"/> maie verie well bée diuided into ſuch as are common to all men, as meate, drinke, &amp; ſuch like: or elſe into ſuch as are vſed but of ſome men, of this kind are games, for all men you knowe, are not gameſters. Concerning the firſt kinde the Apoſtle telleth vs, that the earth is the Lords, &amp; all that there in is. And therefore we maie boldlie féed on anie thing that is ſolde in the Shambles. We maie be bolde I ſaie to delight our taſt with anie kinde of foule that flieth in the aire, with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie kinde of liuing thing that goeth on the earth, with anie kinde of fiſh that liueth in the water, or with anie kinde of fruite that groweth out of the earth. It is lawfull to delight our hearing, our eie-ſight, our ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, our taſt, our féeling: with the vſe of anie thing that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord hath made, for example, it is lawfull to delight our hearing with the ſinging of birds, or with anie other kind of honeſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodie. It is lawfull to delight our eies w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beholding y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glorious maieſtie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heauens, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are drawne out like a cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein.
<pb facs="tcp:2469:15"/> We maie behold the Sun when he commeth out of his chamber, like a bridegrome to run his race, we maie beholde all the hoſt of heauen, and all the glorie of the earth, we may delight our eies with looking vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie amiable coulour or pleaſant ſight, we may take pleaſure in anie freſh &amp; ſwéet ſmelling ſauour. We may féed as I ſaid before on whatſoeuer is pleaſant to our taſt: we maie refreſh our ſelues with heat in Winter, and with cooling things in Summer. And<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4. 1.</note> as the Apoſtle is bolde to call the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddng of anie kinde of meat the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of diuels: Bicauſe the occaſiion of giuing God thankes therefore, is therby taken awaie: ſo I dare boldlie ſaie, that the forbidding a man to refreſh anie of his other ſenſes with anie honeſt delight, is likewiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of diuels, ſo far am I fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning anie honeſt pleaſures. We maie therefore ſport our ſelues as I haue ſaid, or to ſpeake more particularlie, we may with delight view the earth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is apparelled, with flowers, hearbs, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:2469:15"/> trées, &amp; with all kinde of fruite. The incredible multitude wherof is diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed with an inſatiable vareitie, whervnto we maie adde fountaines,<note place="margin">Tullie de natura de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum. 2. booke.</note> goodlie ſprings, cléere waters, riuers, with their gréene bankes. The huge height of mountaines, the largneſſe of the wide fields: to conclude, the whole earth, with the rich treaſures that are hid in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bowels therof, what a come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie grace haue golde and ſiluer aboue other mettels? what alſo and how manie kinde of beaſts are there, both wilde and tame? how trimlie doe the birds fall vpon the earth? the ground is diuided by the diligence of man, ſome to paſture, ſome to tillage, and ſome is taken vp for places to dwell in. The ſea is full of fiſhes, both great &amp; ſmall. If we conſider the beaſts of the earth it is wonderfull, what care the dammes haue to defend their lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ones? how louinglie do the hen ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther her chickins vnder hir wings? Now if we ſhall come to the comelie proportion of euerie liuing thing, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciallie of man, how trimlie are our
<pb facs="tcp:2469:16"/> bones knit together fit, for the mouing and for euerie action of the bodie. The ſences beeing the interpreters &amp; meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of things, are verie fitlie pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head, as it were in a caſtle, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eies as ſpies, poſſeſſe the vppermoſt part of the face, as it were a tower, by their warning the bodie, auoideth manie harmes. All ſounds and all ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours doe naturallie aſſend vpward, our eares therefore and our noſtrels, which are made to receiue ſounds &amp; ſauours, are verie fitlie placed aloft. Our taſt which trieth all thoſe kinde of meates and drinks which we féede on, dwelleth in that part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth, where through all meats and drinks doe goe. Our féeling is diſpearſed throughout our whole bodie, by which meanes, if anie harme come to the bodie by féeling, it maie ſoone be eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied and remedied. Our eies haue a couering which is made ſoft, leaſt our eie ſight ſhould be hurt. Our eares are made winding and haue waxe in them, leaſt by béeing plaine and emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſome thing ſhuld enter in &amp; annoy
<pb facs="tcp:2469:16"/> vs. Our eies are able to iudge of the order and comlineſſe of euerie thing they looke on. Our eares can tel which is a ſwéet, &amp; which is an harſh ſound, wherby were found out ſundrie kind of inſtruments, and the whole art of Muſicke. What our taſt can doe, we are taught by the ſundrie kinde of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes that are dailie deuiſed. With theſe and all ſuch like pleaſant medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations maie we delight our ſelues. Now concerning the right vſe of all theſe thinges that I haue ſpoken of, we ſhall haue a good direction, if wée co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider that they are all the creatures of God, and that we cannot haue the vſe of anie thing which is not his, for he made all, of him, for him, and through him are all thinges, and therefore it is good reaſon that he ſhould be glorified in all. Wée doe not glorifie the Lord in his creatures as we ought to doe, when either wée barre our ſelues to much from the vſe of thoſe thinges that hée hath left fit for vs: or elſe when we vſe them too much. Concerning the firſt
<pb facs="tcp:2469:17"/> kinde we are to-learne that the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God are as ſteps and ſtaires wherby we ariſe to the acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> creator theſe gifts of God, are as it were his hands, whereby he doth lead vs vnto himſelf, that gaue them. But how can we be leade vnto him, when wée refuſe to take him by the hand? how can we be thankfull for that which we caſt a ſide &amp; make no account of? How can we acknowledge the bountifull goodneſſe of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vs, when we refuſe thoſe things which would cauſe vs to haue a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible feeling of it within our ſelues? for this cauſe is the forbidding of meates called the doctrine of diuels. And although this voluntarie abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence may ſéeme to haue a glorious ſhew in the ſight of men: yet the<note place="margin">Coloſ. 2. 16</note> Apoſtle is verie carefull to haue vs take héede of it. And we are to take the better view of this the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles admonition, bicauſe for want of due conſideration thereof, the Pope hath of along time beguiled vs. For though he hath opened a gappe to all
<pb facs="tcp:2469:17"/> kinde of loſeneſſe of life, though hée hath giuen vs great libertie to break all the commandements of God, yet in this matter he hath bene verie ſtrait two daies in euerie wéeke tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough out the yeare, and all the Lent long we might eate neither beaſt, nor foule, nor of any thing that came from either of them. Freſh fiſh, and the che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing meate that is to be ſold at the Poticaries is deere and hard to come by, ſo that the meat that was left vnto vs to feede vpon, was drie &amp; tough ſalt fiſh that hath no wholſome moiſture in it. I remember, <hi>Fuccius</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Phiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in his inſtitutions, ſpeaketh mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie of this matter. It was to be feared (ſaith he) that if the Pope had reigned ouer vs ſtill, he would haue made vs eate haie with the beaſts of the field. This ſtrait charge of the Pope, had a goodlie outward ſhowe: but if wée looke well vpon the matter, we ſhall ſée it was nothing but méere Hipocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. In forbidding theſe meates, the taming of the bodie was pretended: but why then was not wine forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den?
<pb facs="tcp:2469:18"/> Why were not Poticarie Iun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates &amp; delicates taken awaie? which are able to ſet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh aloft more a gret deale, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> béefe, or mutton. Beſide this ſaltfiſh is not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt meate, to prepare our harts to praier as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Papiſts wold make vs beleue: nay, this cold watriſh windie meate, doth trouble &amp; diſquiet our bodie, &amp; maketh vs more vnfit for good meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any other kind of meate. And therefore it is not without good cauſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Apoſtle hath giuen vs this admonitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I denie not, but a man may haue a good meaning in this kind of voluntarie abſtinence, &amp; yet if his ſtraitnes be ouer great he maie offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. <hi>Timothie</hi> was a good man, and yet he did amiſſe, in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he weakened his bodie too much And therefore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth him to drink no longer water, but to vſe a litle wine, for his ſtomackes ſake, &amp; his ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> infirmities. The Lord<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3</note> is not like a couetous houſholder y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelleth his ſeruants to faſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his vit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels might be ſpared, neither doth he enuie vs our meat. He is rich inough, &amp; is alwaies able to giue in great abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2469:18"/> all ſuch things as we haue néed of. Indéed if we abſtain from meat, to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> end we might be more fit to praie, this kind of abſtine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is very accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto him: but if we faint &amp; pine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> too long faſting, ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we cannot pray, or walk in our calling ſo chéere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie as otherwiſe we might, we are the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in as great falt, as if we had ouer eate our ſelues, or as if by ouer drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelues, we were made vnfit to do anie good thing, &amp; therfore when fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded vnto vs in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, praier is alwaies ioined withall. The heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> philoſophers, eſpeciallie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Stoicks, were wont to ſpeak very co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptuouſlie of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities of this life: but yet we Chriſtians like neuer awhit y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which were not delighted with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities of this preſent life, were not ſet vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a better life: but we make ſome account of them: &amp; although in reſpect of Chriſt, we account all the world as dounge: yet otherwiſe we take them as ſignes and ſcales of the fauourable loue of God towards vs.
<pb facs="tcp:2469:19"/> By them we are aſſured that he hath greater goods in ſtore for vs, againſt ſuch time as he ſhall take vs vnto himſelfe. We maie alſo abuſe the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures of God, by vſing of them too much: for whether we eat or drinke, or whatſoeuer we doe, we muſt do all<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10. 31</note> to the glorie of God. And therefore when the lawfull vſe of meats and drinkes is ſet downe in the ſcripture, there is alſo mention made of giuing<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4. 4 Rom. 14. 6.</note> of thankes: but when we ſtuffe our bodies, with meates and drinkes, the heart is kept downe ſo, that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not aſcend vnto the acknowledging of the giuer. When we put on gorge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous or curious apparell, to maruaile at our ſelues and to contemne other, we cannot be thankfull. For, how can thankfulneſſe proceed from a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuous and a proud heart? How can we lift vp a thankfull heart vnto the creator, when we ſtaie ſo much in the creature it ſelfe that we are neuer ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfied therewith? For this cauſe are we commanded if riches increaſe, not to ſet our hearts vpon them. Looke
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2469:19"/> not (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) vpon the wine<note place="margin">Pro. 23 31.</note> when it is red, and when it ſheweth his colour in the cup, or goeth downe pleaſantlie, we muſt not make a God of our bellie, for we read, that the Iewes that had ſuch a greedie deſire to their meate, died with Quailes in their mouthes. For though a man haue abundaunce, yet his life ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not in his riches: Man liueth not by bread, but by the prouidence of God. It was ſaid to the rich man that reioiced ſo much in his riches, and ſaid to his ſoule, Soule thou haſt<note place="margin">Luke. 12. 17</note> much goods laid vp for manie yeres, liue at eaſe, eate, drinke, and take thy paſtime: O foole, this night will I fetch awaie thy ſoule from thée, then whoſe ſhal thoſe things be which thou haſt prouided? The Lord doth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times of purpoſe leſſen thoſe meanes wherby he wil ſaue vs, leaſt we ſhuld ſtaie our ſelues too much vpon them: for this cauſe, the Lord doth ſtrike the<note place="margin">Iudg 7, 2.</note> earth with barrenneſſe, leaſt our minde ſhould bée too much buſied in thinking what great crops we haue
<pb facs="tcp:2469:20"/> had: for this cauſe by ſicknes he dot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> often take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vigor of our taſt &amp; doth mingle all our pleaſures with griefe, as it were with an vnſauerie tongue as the booke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preacher tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs. He ſometimes taketh from vs our wiſe counſellers, our valiant &amp; politicke capitanes. He ſometimes ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth earthquakes. He beateth down our ſtrong holdes &amp; caſtels, &amp; all our munition of war, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end we might ſee what a vaine thing it is to truſt in any earthlie defenſe. An horſe ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet is but a vaine thing to ſaue a mans life. It is but a vaine thing to truſt in Princes, for except the Lord kéepe the citie, the kéeper watcheth in vaine. Our truſt therefore muſt be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of God, that made both heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 127.</note> &amp; earth, thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> truſt in him ſhalbe as mount <hi>Sion,</hi> which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be remoued but remaineth for euer. Héere alone doth the difference conſiſt betweene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> child of God, &amp; a naturall man: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> child of God, hath his hart knit vnto him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> made all things: but the natural man is altogether linked to the creature,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2469:20"/> they make it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place, where all their affections haue their abode, it is their <hi>Summu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bonum,</hi> it is their happines, it is their onlie ioie. The philoſophers wer verie diligent markers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie properties that wer in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> creatures of God, they ſpake verie plentifullie of the vertue of hearbs &amp; mettals, &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nature of euerie liuing thing. They knewe by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> creatures y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there was a God, yet did they neuer worſhip him as God, neither were they thankfull, but became vain in their imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; their fooliſh hart was ful of darknes. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>Tullie</hi> their chiefe Orator, in his<note place="margin">Rom. 1. 21.</note> booke <hi>De natura deoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> when he had diſcourſed at large, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great wiſdom &amp; bountifulnes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was to by ſéene in the workmanſhip of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> creatures, yet as if he had bene halfe a god himſelf, or onlie an idle looker on, &amp; had no be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he vſeth not one word of thankſgiuing. He was a very eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t man, &amp; had tounge at will, yet whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhuld come to ſound foorth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> praiſe of God, he was altogether ſpeachles: but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> intreting of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame
<pb facs="tcp:2469:21"/> matter, breaketh out into thankfull ſpeaches. O Lord ſaith he, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold are thy workes? In wiſedome haſt thou made them all: the earth is full of thy riches. And againe, I will ſing vnto the Lord all my life, I will praiſe my God while I liue. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, O my ſoule praiſe thou the Lord, Praiſe ye the Lord. Likewiſe<note place="margin">Pſal. 104.</note> in the 8. Pſalme, O Lord, our Lord, how excellent is thy name in all the world? His whole Pſalmes are full of ſuch meditations, for this thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe that I ſpeake of, was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies the foote of his ſong. O that the Papiſts would but aduiſedlie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this thankfulneſſe of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Dauid,</hi> our controuerſie then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Organes, &amp; chaunting of ſongs, would ſoone be at an ende. They can readilie alleadge, all the kinde of inſtruments that <hi>Dauid</hi> vſed, but they will neuer remember withall, that he praiſed the Lord in them. They maie vnderſtand if they will, by the 14. of the firſt to the <hi>Corinths,</hi> that there was made a diſtinction in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2469:21"/> the ſoundes, and that the people knew what was piped, and what was harp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.<note place="margin">Pſa. 106. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> But they think it maketh no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter though Engliſh men ſing a ſong in the Latine tongue that they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not. The note is the thing that they take pleaſure in, ſo that as we ſée they ſing not to the Lord, but to their owne eares. And that makes them ſpeake ſo baſelie of our ſongs. We all with one voice in a plaine and diſtinct note ſing luſtelie vnto the Lord with a good courage. And that they like not of, their hearts are ſet vpon the melodie of the deſcant: they worſhip him that made the note, they doe not ſing to the Lord. Where do they finde that the ſongs of <hi>Dauid,</hi> vſed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God, were of fiue or ſix parts? Where doe they finde that they qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered and deuided the note ſo, that the people could not vnderſtand what was ſung. In the 25. of the firſt booke of the Chronicles, the order of muſick that the Iewes vſed in the ſeruice of God is ſet down, but there is no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uch babbling muſicke.
<pb facs="tcp:2469:22"/> The end wherefore their ſongs were ſung, is directlie againſt this chaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>1. Chro. 16.</hi> the. 4. &amp;. 7. verſe. The Lord will be worſhipped in ſpirit &amp; in truth. And if we will ſing <hi>Dauids</hi> Pſalmes, we muſt bring <hi>Dauids</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, or els the Lord cares not for our melodie. Our delight muſt not reſt in anie thing but in the Lord, he is the Lord our God, &amp; we muſt haue none other Gods but him. The Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hath commaunded vs to honour thoſe that he hath ſet ouer vs, &amp; the Apoſtle teacheth vs, that it is the firſt commandement w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a promiſe to obay our parents. And yet he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> loueth fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or mother better then Chriſt, is not worthie of him. He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> taketh more pleſure in his parents then in Chriſt, is reiected of him. Likewiſe we muſt haue in eſtimation the miniſters of the word for their works ſake, yet we<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3. 21.</note> muſt not abſolutelie reſt our ſelues vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we muſt not reioice in me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but we muſt reioice in God y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by men. Now if the Lord will not haue vs depend too much vpon men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:2469:22"/> ſowe into our hearts y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> immortall and<note place="margin">Pſa. 014</note> incorruptible ſéed of eternal life: how greatlie ſhal we think wil it diſpleaſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, to delight ſo much in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil<note place="margin">1. Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> things of this world which periſh with the vſe? We maie reioice (as I ſaid before) in vſing theſe corruptible creatures of God, for wine maketh glad the heart of man (as the Prophet ſaith) but yet we muſt reioice as if we reioiced not. For if it be too vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Lord cannot awaie withall. Woe be vnto you (ſaith Chriſt) that<note place="margin">Lu. 6. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> are rich, for you haue receiued your conſolation, woe be vnto you that are full, for you ſhall hunger, woe be to you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> now laugh, for you ſhall waile and wéepe. They lie vpon beds of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorie (ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophet <hi>Amos)</hi> &amp; ſtretch themſelues vpon their beds, &amp; eat the Lambes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flocke, &amp; the Calues out of the ſtall, they ſing to the ſound of the violl. They inuent to themſelues inſtruments of Muſicke like <hi>Dauid. Dauid</hi> was neuer ſo buſie in deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Inſtrumentes to ſerue Gods glorie, as they were in deuiſing
<pb facs="tcp:2469:23"/> of them to ſerue their wanton luſts. It is lawfull no doubt to laugh. It<note place="margin">King. 18.</note> is lawfull to eate a fat Lambe or a fat Calfe. It is lawfull to delight our ſelues with muſicke, for the earth is the Lords, as the Apoſtle ſaith. Yet vnto that people y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bathed themſelues in theſe pleaſures, that wallowed &amp; laid themſelues downe in them, neuer remembring the Lord that gaue them, theſe terrible woes of the Prophet are thundered againſt. The reaſon why the rich glutton béeing in tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uke. 16, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uke. 8.</note> could receiue no comfort was, becauſe of the pleaſures that he enioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this world. Remember (ſaith <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham)</hi> that thou in thy life time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuedſt thy pleaſure, &amp; likewiſe <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> paines, now therefore is hée comforted, and thou art tormented. And we are to conſider that one kinde of men that heare the word vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tablie, and remaine ſtill in their cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed eſtate, are thoſe into whoſe hearts voluptuous liuing enters in, &amp; makes the ſéede vnfruitefull. And therefore Chriſt our Sauiour ſetting downe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2469:23"/> vnto vs the ſuddainneſſe of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, willeth vs in anie caſe to take héede of ſurfetting and dronkenneſſe. I would to God, we would wiſelie conſider of this admonition, we ſhuld not then ſurfet as we doe, we ſhould not then haue ſo manie and ſo ſundry kindes of diſhes as we haue. Wée vſe to ſaie, doe not men knowe when they haue eate inough, and maie not a man eate of ſundrie diſhes without ſurfetting? They alwaies marke what maie be done, but they neuer conſider what is like to be done, and what is commonlie done. They think that becauſe no man will be knowne of it, when hée hath eaten too much, that therefore men ſeldome or neuer ouer eate themſelues: But our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt would haue vs to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect our ſelues. He giueth vs a watch word, Take héede, ſaith hée: If there were no daunger in the matter, this warning had bene in vaine. How is it poſſible but that at our feaſting, as we vſe the matter, we ſhould offend againſt this commaundement of
<pb facs="tcp:2469:24"/> Chriſt? Firſt we muſt haue brawne and muſcadine, next to that we muſt haue ſtewde meate, (the reſt of our meat muſt not be ſéene all this while) when men haue wel dined with theſe two ſeruices, then muſt we haue roſt meate and baked meate: laſt of all, we muſt haue a newe dinner with ſundrie kinde of fruits. I graunt at ſuch méetings we maie haue a more liberal diet then we wer accuſtomed, neither are ſundrie kindes of meates to be miſliked of, if they come round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in together, ſo that euerie man maie eate where he thinketh good. But if our ſundrie diſhes, come at ſuch ſundrie times, with ſuch a pauſe betwéene them, it is a thouſand to one, that we ſhall breake this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement. It is not for naught, that the godlie man <hi>Iob</hi> was afraid that his ſonnes had offended at their banketting. This rioting ſetteth vs altogether vpon the hoigh, it ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth from our hearts the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our owne vileneſſe, and ſo long as we are thus aloft, we can haue no
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2469:24"/> thankfull remembraunce of him that gaue theſe things vnto vs, for thankes giuing if it be in truth, is done with the beating downe of the heart, and with abaſing of our ſelues. And therfore the wiſe man ſaith, It is better to goe to the houſe of mourning: then to the houſe of feaſting: this reaſon that I ſpeake of is added, becauſe ſaith he, this is the ende of all men, and the liuing ſhall laie it to his heart. And againe, Anger is better then laughter: for by a ſad looke the heart is made better. The hart of the wiſe<note place="margin">Preac. 7. 4.</note> is in the houſe of mourning: but the heart of fooles, is in the houſe of mirth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Demas.</speaker>
                  <p>The proofes that you haue brought are plaine proofes, I cannot ſaie againſt it: And yet I haue a probable reaſon, which maie ſéeme to make ſomewhat againſt that which you haue ſaide, my reaſon is this. I thinke, you nor no man els of anie iudgement, will denie, that he that teacheth, that it is not
<pb facs="tcp:2469:25"/> lawfull for anie man, at anie time to eate anie kinde of meate (ſo that in the forbidding thereof reſpect be not had to the common wealth) ſetteth downe the doctrine of diuels, although he neither forbid all kinde of meate, nor at all times, nor to all men. How then can you ſaie, that it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, when one hath comforted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſufficientlie with ſome kinde of meat, to haue the vſe of new delicates without béeing in the like fault?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>The Papiſts I graunt you in forbidding fleſh and white meat in Lent, and in forbidding Prieſts (as they call them) to marrie, taught the doctrine of diuels. For they forbadde meates, they forbadde marriage. And although they forbadde not meate at all times, nor marriage to all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, yet they forbadde both: and as Maiſter <hi>Iewel</hi> telleth them, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis &amp; minus non mutant ſpeciem.</hi> For as he that killeth a fewe men, is a murtherer: ſo he that forbiddeth meate at ſome time of the yeare, forbideth meate.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2469:25"/> But I doe not forbid anie meate to anie man, at anie time. For when I ſee a man that hath eaten inough, and yet is readie to eate more, if I forbid him, and tell him it is gluttonie to do ſo: doe I by ſo ſaieng forbid anie kinde of meat? Who ſéeth not that I forbid the ſtuffing of his bodie with gorge vpon gorge, and not anie kinde of meat, for if his ſtomake were emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the meate were lawfull inough, euen at that time, for that perſon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Demas.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet I doe not ſée how you can call it vnlawfull, when a man ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céedeth in eating. For where is then that difference, betwéene lawfull and<note place="margin">1. Co. 10. 29</note> expedient that the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>The Apoſtles meaning was not to tell vs, that abuſing of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie indifferent thing was onelie not expedient, but not vnlawfull. His purpoſe was not to make anie ſuch nice diſtinction, but onelie this, that all indifferent things, though in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues they were lawfull, yet the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtaunces might make them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull.
<pb facs="tcp:2469:26"/> The Apoſtle beſtoweth thrée or foure whole Chapters, in teaching the <hi>Romanes</hi> and the <hi>Corinthes,</hi> how to vſe indifferent things. He telleth<note place="margin">Cor. 8. 12.</note> the <hi>Corinthes,</hi> that by vſing their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie too much, they did ſinne againſt Chriſt, ſo that as we ſée, they ſaie no thing, which when a thing is indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, ſaie it maketh no matter how it bée done.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>Of gaming. The ſecond Chapter.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DEmas.</speaker>
                  <p>You haue ſpoken ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie of thoſe pleaſures that are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all men: ſpeake I praie you in like manner, of ſuch as are v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed but of ſome men, of gaming I meane.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>Gaming is an exerciſe, which a man taketh in hand to delight himſelfe withall. By calling it an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, I make a difference betwéene it, and other pleaſures that are alre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die ſpoken of, for we do not vſe to call eating, drinking, ſmelling, and ſuch like delightes, by the name of exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2469:26"/> And I make a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene it and the continuall exerciſes which we dailie labour in, when I ſaie, that the ende of gaming is to delight a man withall, for other exerciſes doe eſpeciallie reſpect pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Demas.</speaker>
                  <p>I praie you ſir, what thinke you of this matter? ſome me thinke are verie ſtrait which would not haue vs ſpend one minute of an houre in anie recreation: they bring their reaſon out of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,<note place="margin">Ephe. 5. 16.</note> which would haue vs redéeme the time, becauſe the daies are euill.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>It is a cléere caſe, that a man doth redéeme the time ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entlie, when hée maketh anie lawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full delight, an occaſion to lift vp a thankfull minde vnto God for it. And it is certeine, that the dumpiſh ſadneſſe which drieth vp a mans bones doth diſpleaſe the Lord. The Lord was not one whitte diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the inwarde fretting, and<note place="margin">1. Kings. 21. 4.</note> penſiueneſſe of wicked king <hi>Achab.</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:2469:27"/> He liketh well inough of a merrie and chéerefull countenaunce, and if a mans talke be wittie, and hath no vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſauerie vanitie in it, though it be ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, the Scripture will beare a man out in it well inough. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, thus much one maie well ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by that place. Bicauſe men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monlie run at riot, and make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues dronken with delighting in the creatures: For this cauſe the children of God ought to vſe them warilie, that as on the one ſide, the euill example of manie is of great force to drawe them to inordinate deſire to them: ſo on the other ſide, their watchfull &amp; warie taking héed, ſhould be as forcible to driue them to godlie moderation in them, &amp; this is it that the Apoſtle calleth the redéeming of the time. Now, concerning gaming, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end we maie know what games are lawfull, and what are vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, we are to conſider, that all games whatſoeuer, muſt be made ſutable to the commaundement, they muſt agrée in euerie point with Chriſtian doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2469:27"/> Euen an heathen man by the light of nature could ſée, that this rule<note place="margin">Tullie. 2. his office, 1. booke.</note> is to be obſerued, and therfore it is a ſhame, that we Chriſtians ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe it Our plaie, ſaith he, muſt not be, <hi>Alienus ab honeſtatis actionibus.</hi> Séeing therfore this rule muſt ſtand, we maie be bolde to condemne all the whole rable and rout of games that are vſed at Chriſtmas as we call it. We know that Chriſt was neuer anie Chriſtmas Lord, he was neuer Lord of miſrule, whie then doe we ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate his feaſt with vnrulie ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming? Towards Chriſtmas the ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers maie ſhutte their maiſter out of ſchoole. A fellowe whome they call the Chriſtmas Lord, maie bée checkmate with his betters. But the Lord Ieſus would haue vs to ſhew in outward behauiour, that reuerend eſtimation that we haue of our ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours in our hearts. This vnruly fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, maie cauſe thoſe which offend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his vnrulie lawes, to haue ten pound and a purſe, to be ſtockt or pumpt, which they call beheadding.
<pb facs="tcp:2469:28"/> At this time, if men can get a ſimple fellow, &amp; put him to paine with mum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a ſparrow, they thinke it is trim ſport. At an other time of the yeare, women haue a daie, which they call rock mundaie, then vſe they to binde, and otherwiſe to abuſe ſuch men as<note place="margin">Deut. 22. 7.</note> they can maſter, but our Ieſus Chriſt abhorreth all kinde of crueltie. Hée will not haue vs deale cruellie, no not with little birdes, how much more then doth he hate it towardes men, which are made according to his owne Image? There be alſo games that be filthie which tend to the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> commaundement wherin all vncleanenes is forbidden. Of this kinde are our light kinde of daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, ſawing of gréene timber, ſeruing men in ſackes, and ſuch like. But the Lord Chriſt commandeth vs to haue<note place="margin">Mat. 5.</note> chaſt hearts, chaſt eies, &amp; chaſt hands. The Lord ſo abhorreth this ribaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> when men ſtriue together one with an other, if the wife of the one come néere for to rid hir huſband out of the hands of him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſmiteth him, &amp;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2469:28"/> putteth foorth hir hand, and take him by his priuities, then ſaith the Lord<note place="margin">Deu. 25. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> to the magiſtrate, thou ſhalt cut off hir hand: thine eie ſhall not ſpare hir. We ſée the ſelfe ſame filthineſſe that we vſe, was reuenged with the loſſe of a hand, notwithſtanding the partie that offended ment thereby to deliuer hir huſband from violence. Wée haue games alſo which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in getting moneie one from an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and yet the Lorde Chriſt hath forbidden all couetous deſires. Wée haue games wherein we make ſome or other laughing ſtockes to the whole companie. Of this kinde are hinch, pinch, and laugh not, and ſuch like: But the Lorde Chriſt would haue vs mainteine as much as wée can, the good report of our brother: and how is this done when wée goe about to make the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie beléeue, that hée is a foole, and deſerueth to be laughed at. In the fiue and twentie of <hi>Deuteronomie</hi> wée are commaunded to kéepe a moderation in correcting a man,
<pb facs="tcp:2469:29"/> although he doth deſerue, and ought to be puniſhed, leaſt he ſhould ſéeme deſpiſed in our ſight, how much more ought we to auoide this thing, when our brother hath not offended? Wée<note place="margin">Leui. 19. 14</note> muſt not ſpeake euill to him that is deafe, the Lord vnder this one kinde forbiddeth vs to twit our brother by anie of his infirmities or wants, we therefore ſinne againſt the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, when by anie kinde of ſport we vpbraide him with ſimplicitie, and want of wit, we ought to be féete to the lame, and eies to the blinde,<note place="margin">Iob. 29. 15.</note> wiſdome to the fooliſh, and not vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braide them with their wants. Men I knowe will make but a light mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of it, for fooles count it but a ſport to ſinne, they think there is no harme done, except there be an arme or a legge broken. But the Lord doth make more account of his commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement then ſo. When <hi>Adam</hi> had eaten of the forbidden trée, there was no harme done, as they call harme. Yet this ſinne, that they make ſo light account of, waied him downe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2469:29"/> to the pit of hell, and if he had not had a redéemer, he and all his poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſhould moſt certeinlie haue bene ſwallowed vp of eternall confuſion, and Chriſt came not to deſtroie the lawe, but to fulfill it. Whoſoeuer ſaith Chriſt, breaketh the leaſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement<note place="margin">Mat. 5.</note> and teacheth men ſo, he ſhall be leaſt in the kingdome of God, that is to ſaie, hée ſhall not bée in the kindgome of God at all, for it followeth immediatlie, Except your righteouſneſſe excéede the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Scribes and Phareſies, ye ſhall not enter into the kingdome of heauen: and wée knowe that their righteouſnes had reſpect to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward murther, to outward theft, till heauen and earth periſh, one iotte or title of the lawe ſhall not ſcape, till all thinges be fulfilled. I read not long ſince a learned &amp; a godlie trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, wherein is conteined a ſpeach belonging to this matter, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is excellent, and becauſe a notable iudgement of God did fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe vpon the preaching thereof,
<pb facs="tcp:2469:30"/> which did as it were from heauen, féele the truth of it, I will repeate it vnto you. Hath Ieſus Chriſt come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fleſh to laie the bridle of our necks, to runne after our owne vaine deuiſes? Hath he obtained by his comming twelue daies of God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for carding, diſing, maſking, muming, for mocking and mowing, for crieng and laughing, for the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſing of euerie vaine deuiſe that commeth to our heads all the yeare. Or doe we thinke that this propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of ſo earneſt a matter, this tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the grace of God into li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence and wantonneſſe, ſhall be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed? What is this but euen to giue a réede into the hand of Ieſus Chriſt, and to mocke his kingdome? What crowning of him is it in this vaine mirth and wantonneſſe, but with briers and thornes to pricke his head? Is this the ioie ſpoken off by the Angell that came to declare his birth, tolde hée tidinges of this gladneſſe? Is this the benefite that thou haſt purchaſed to vs by that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2469:30"/> wonderfull myſterie of thine incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, O <hi>Emmanuel?</hi> Oh I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed that it ſhould euer be hearde of among the Iewes and Turkes, that the Chriſtians at that time of the yeare when their ſauiour was borne, ſhuld giue themſelues for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie daies, from their ordinarie mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, and ſhamefaced behauiour, from walking ordinarilie in their vocation &amp; ſtudies, to vnmodeſt &amp; ſhamefull practiſes, to vnmodeſt &amp; waking, &amp; all for vaine &amp; vnfruitfull works of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Wherin differeth our celebrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the natiuitie of Chriſt from the popiſh Chriſtians? How doe we looke to call Papiſts from their vaine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are not our ſelues a foot from them? I think if but thus much were ſpoken amongſt the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then againſt ſo great an abuſe, they would repent in ſackcloth and aſhes. And yet I know that this people will not be brought from this vaine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, for they loue it and delight in that: without theſe thinges, they complaine that it is but a dead
<pb facs="tcp:2469:31"/> Chriſtmas. Theſe men will neuer confeſſe the truth of this doctrine, till God haue ſealed it with ſome plague or other. This plague of God was threatened by a godlie learned young man in a ſermon that he made at Trinitie Colledge, ſomewhat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſtmas, after Chriſtmas the plague that was threatened fell. For a ſcholler of Trinitie Colledge ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled himſelfe right ouer the place where he with other kept ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell route. Who is wiſe ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> and will marke theſe thinges? The ſinne which before ſéemed as light as a feather, did then lie hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie at his heart, his merrie compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions could not take awaie the ſting thereof from him, this ſinne ſo troubled his minde, that the violent renting aſunder of the ſoule from the vodie, ſéemed nothing ſo grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous, nay, hée vſed this violent ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that I ſpeake off as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie to eaſe himſelfe of the other. The Lord would awake vs by this his fearefull iudgement out of our
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2469:31"/> déepe ſléepe of ſinne, leaſt we ſhould go to hell as it were in a ſléepe before we are aware of it, and yet wée are ſtill fooliſh, and can take no profit by it. Becauſe theſe iudgements of God come ſo ſeldome, wée ſoone forgette them: but if the Lorde ſhould thus dailie puniſh vs, wée would not thinke that there is anie iudgement to come. Becauſe this fearfull plague was not executed vpon our own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, we are therefore without feare: but it pleaſeth the Lord to admoniſh vs by this his iudgement: and how could this thing haue bene, if we our ſelues had bene thus puniſhed: wée thinke we haue wit inough to auoide this thing, but in thinking ſo wée thinke amiſſe, for the Scholler had wit inough: and if hée had not, I am ſure <hi>Achitophel</hi> had, and yet did he thus violentlie deſtroie himſelfe. When the iudgements of God fall vpon vs, all the witte we haue can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not auoide them, the onelie waie to auoide the fearefull iudgements of God, is to forſake our rioting, which
<pb facs="tcp:2469:32"/> is the cauſe thereof.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of continuance at gaming. The third Chapter.</head>
               <p>BVt I will goe forward and ſpeake more particulerlie of gaming, Games me think maie verie well be diuided into ſuch, the chiefe ſport whereof conſiſteth in looking on, of which kinde, are hunting, hawking, ſtage plaies, and ſuch like. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch wherein men are the chiefe dooers, of which kinde are daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, dicing, teneſing, and ſuch like.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Demas.</speaker>
                  <p>I praie you ſir, what thinke you of hunting? doe you thinke it an vnméet exerciſe for a Chriſtian? I haue heard that ſome haue vtterlie diſalowed of it, becauſe <hi>Eſau</hi> a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedman hunted.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſome men doe I cannot tell, for my part I dare not condemne it: as for the reaſon of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau,</hi> his hunting it is nothing worth.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2469:32"/> For as euerie thing that a godlie man doth, is not by and by to bée allowed off, ſo is not euerie thing that a wicked man doth alwaies to be miſliked. Beſide this, though <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau</hi> béeing a wicked man hunted, yet he did it at the commandement of his father which was a good man, my rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon wherefore it ought not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned is this. The Lord hath giuen the free vſe of all his creatures to vs Chriſtians, wée maie ſafelie féede of them all. In giuing therfore the vſe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he alloweth of the meanes wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we come to haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe of them, for otherwiſe he ſhould but mocke vs. Onelie the faultes of hunters and fawkners I will not take vpon me to defende. The ſpoiling of mens doue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes for the prouiſion of their hawkes, the ſpoiling of mens corne, with the entring of their hawkes, at the beginning of harueſt, the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of gaps, whereby mens ground is laide open to the ſpoile, theſe thinges cannot bée allowed off, for if the Lorde cannot abide that wée
<pb facs="tcp:2469:33"/> ſhould profit our ſelues by the hurt of an other, he can much leſſe abide that for our pleaſure we ſhould be an hinderaunce to anie. The gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall thing that is to be obſerued in all games is this, that no man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowe too much time in them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they be lawfull, for euerie man without exception, muſt buiſie himſelfe in ſome certeine &amp; dailie cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, but thoſe that followe gaming cannot doe ſo: therfore no man muſt followe gaming. But to the ende it might bée knowne what I meane, I tearme this a calling (not to paie to euerie man that which is his, or to doe as a man would bée done to,) for that is a generall thing wherevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all men are called, but dailie to exerciſe himſelfe in ſome certeine trade to the profit of others, this is it which I terme a calling. But becauſe you do not yet vnderſtand my minde, I will ſpeak more plainlie. This cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling which I ſpeake off conſiſteth either of the dailie laboure of the minde, or of the dailie trauell of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2469:33"/> bodie. Thoſe callings which conſiſt of the labour of the minde, are Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, Lawe, or Diuinitie. He which doth diligentlie ſéeke wiſelie to applie thoſe Phiſicke helpes which the Lord hath apointed for the preſeruing or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of our health, he behaueth him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe well in his calling. In the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Lawe likewiſe, he which bendeth his pleading, his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelling or giuing of ſentence, to this ende that euerie man maie enioie that which is his, he liueth well in a good calling. In Diuinitie he which féedeth his flocke diligentlie, liueth honeſtlie in an honeſt calling. He I ſaie which exerciſeth himſelfe paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie in anie of theſe profeſſions, or teacheth the tongues, or anie liberall art, whereby men maie be made fitte to practiſe more profitablie anie of theſe profeſſions. He liueth in an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt calling: the like maie be ſaid of anie occupation or bodilie trauell, whereby the neceſſities of this preſent life are conuaied vnto our bretheren. But euerie bodie will not graunt me
<pb facs="tcp:2469:34"/> that euery man is bound to labour in ſome one and certeine calling, and therefore I will ſtand ſomewhat in the proofe of it. The Scripture ſaith, that man is borne vnto trauell. And<note place="margin">Iob. 5.</note> it was ſaid to <hi>Adam,</hi> and in him to all his ofſpring, In the ſweate of thy<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> face ſhalt thou eate thy bread. Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie man will graunt that this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, laieth holde of that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of <hi>Adam</hi> that is poore, and not otherwiſe able to mainteine it ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>But whether it laieth hold of thoſe that haue ſufficient to followe their pleaſures, that is a queſtion with ſome. Belike they thinke that if a man haue enough for himſelfe he née<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not to haue anie care of other. Euerie man for himſelfe as they ſaie, and God for vs all. But whoſoeuer ſaith ſo, God will not ſubſcribe to this their ſaieng, for it is flatte con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to his commaundement. Loue ſaith the Apoſtle is the fulfilling of the Lawe, not that loue that hath
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2469:34"/> reſpecte to himſelfe, but that loue that hath reſpecte to others.</p>
                  <p>And the Scripture bindeth him<note place="margin">Ephe. 4. 28.</note> that liueth euen of his handie worke to labour, that he maie haue to giue<note place="margin">2. Cor. 8. 13.</note> vnto him that néedeth, neither yet was it the Apoſtles minde, that others ſhould bée eaſed, and hée grieued, but that that which remained of the honeſt prouiſion for him and his, ſhould bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vppon ſuch as haue more néede, of ſuch I ſaie, as either by reaſon of age, or ſickneſſe, coulde not labour for their owne mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce.</p>
                  <p>Now, if the Apoſtle aſketh thus much at the handes of a labouring man: ſhall wée not thinke that hée would haue that money which is ſpent vppon ſuperfluous gaming beſtowed vppon the poore? If this be true, as it is moſt true, then is not a man to make an ordinarie trade in ſporting himſelfe anie waie, ſéeing that aſketh great charges,
<pb facs="tcp:2469:35"/> which might be beſtowed much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vpon thoſe that haue neede. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is he onlie to abſtaine from theſe néedleſſe expences: but he is alſo to ſée that his houſe be well gouerned. He is to haue a care not onelie to thoſe reuenewes which he hath: but alſo by all honeſt meanes to increaſe them, not that he might enlarge his worldlie delights, but that hee might haue to miniſter to ſuch as haue need, as the Apoſtle commandeth. In the laſt chapter of the Prouerbs, where the properties of a vertuous woman are ſet down, it is ſaid, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe laboureth chéerefullie with her hands: And leſt ſome ſhould cauill, and ſaie, the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeaketh of a poore woman which could not otherwiſe liue. We are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to vnderſtand, that it ſpeaketh of a wealthie woman, ſhe maketh her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe carpets ſaith the text: fine lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen and purple is her garment, ſhée ſtretcheth out her hand to the poore, and putteth foorth her hand to the née<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. Naie, though there ſhould come no profite either to a mans own ſelfe,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2469:35"/> or to anie other, yet labour is ſo well pleaſing in the ſight of God, that he will haue a man occupied in it. Hée will not haue a mans minde wander about he cannot tell what. In the ſweat of thy face ſhalt thou eate thy bread, ſaith he vnto <hi>Adam,</hi> although he had all the earth before him, and had none to prouide for, but for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his wife. Euen before man ſinned, when the earth brought foorth all things of her owne accord, when there was no néede to labour, yet the Lord would not haue him liue idlie, but put him in the garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> that he might dreſſe and kéepe it, how then dare we ſaie that a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and one that hath inough, maie liue idlie, and as he liſt? Doth not the Scripture tell vs plainlie that the<note place="margin">Ezech. 16.</note> ſinnes of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorre,</hi> were pride, fulneſſe of bread, and abundance of idleneſſe? Doeth not I ſaie, the Scripture tell vs, that idleneſſe was one of thoſe faults, which pulled fire and brimſtone from heauen vpon the ſtinking <hi>Sodomites?</hi> The Cities of
<pb facs="tcp:2469:36"/> 
                     <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorre</hi> were fruite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Cities, they were as the garden of the Lord like the land of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> as thou goeſt vnto <hi>Zoar,</hi> and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple thereof had as little neede to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for their commodities by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the fruitfulneſſe of the ſoile, as anie people vnder the Sunne: yet was idleneſſe one cauſe of their deſtruction. Why then ſhould a man that hath all commodities brought him to his hand, thinke he maie liue idlie? There is no man whom the Lord hath created for naught. Hée will haue euerie one placed in ſome calling, that one maie bée for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of another: thoſe therefore that followe gaming what doe they but trouble the order that God hath appointed. And therefore the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaking of thoſe that liued idlie, ſaith, that they liued inordinatelie:<note place="margin">2. The. 3. 11</note> thereby he giueth vs to vnderſtand, that it is an order ſet downe by the Lord, that euerie one ſhould labour. But men are meruailous ſuttle now a daies, and verie cunning to deceiue
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2469:36"/> themſelues. They will eaſilie graunt you that a man which ſitteth buzzing all daie long liueth idlie: but hée which vſeth ſuch pleaſures as aſke the exerciſe of the bodie though hée doeth nothing els, yet it will not ſinke into their heades that ſuch a one liueth idlie. Shall we thinke then that the idle <hi>Sodomites</hi> did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but lie and tumble all daie long? Naie, the Scripture telleth vs that an idle bodie doth occupie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe more in his kinde then anie labouring man. Hée maketh a ſigne with his eies, hée ſignifieth with his féete, hée inſtructeth with his fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, lewde things are in his heart, hée imagineth euill at all times, and raiſeth vp contention ſaith the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Ghoſt. The Apoſtle calleth thoſe which liued idlie buſie bodies. And none commonlie meddle more with other mens matters, then thoſe that haue no buſineſſe of their owne. You ſhall heare them talke of anie<note place="margin">Pro. 6. 13.</note> thing that can come in queſtion, for as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, A ſluggarde is<note place="margin">2. The. 3. 11.</note>
                     <pb facs="tcp:2469:37"/> wiſer in his owne conceipt, then ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen men that can render a reſon. We ſée therefore, contrarie to that which they ſuppoſe, that a man maie liue idlie and yet be occupied. When wée haue done our neceſſarie affaires, we vſe to ſaie, that we are at leaſure to doe ſuch things, as are not of the like importaunce: but hée which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies thus at leaſure, what is he but alwaies idle, notwithſtanding hée moue his bodie ſometimes. For what other thing is idleneſſe, but not to buſie a mans ſelfe about ſame profit. He which plaieth at football or at ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, though for the time he laboureth as ſore as he doth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> goeth to plough: yet we make a difference betwéene theſe labours, for the one is a trauell, and the other is a recreation: of the one there commeth ſome profite: the other is but a paſtime: ſo that though we moue our bodies, yet we maie bée idle. And if we will define idleneſſe to be a continuall quietneſſe both of the bodie and of the minde: we ſhall not finde out an idle bodie in the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2469:37"/> whole world euen <hi>Sardanapalus</hi> was neuer ſo idle, but that he would ſpin ſometimes amongſt his harlottes. Neither doe I thinke that there was euer anie glutton ſo lazie, but that hée would exerciſe his bodie ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times before meales, to make his meate goe downe more pleaſauntlie. He alone maie trulie be ſaid to be no idle bodie, which betaketh himſelfe to ſome ordinarie trade. He (I ſaie) which giueth not himſelfe libertie to doe whatſoeuer his wandring head ſhall by fittes moue him vnto: but ſetteth downe ſome certeine, and dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie kinde of exerciſing, either his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die or minde to the profit of others, and tieth himſelfe thereto, ſuch a one liueth in an honeſt calling. A man maie vſe recreations, as I ſaid before: but this honeſt calling that I ſpeake of, muſt haue the chiefe part of his life. It muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies haue the vpper hand, we ſée that huſbandmen and all ſuch as vſe anie honeſt trade are an helpe vnto vs: For by them the neceſſities of
<pb facs="tcp:2469:38"/> this preſent life are conuaied vnto vs: But an idle bodie, what good doeth hée? Why is it ſette downe in the Scripture that <hi>Caine, Abel, Noah, Lot, Iſaacke,</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> were huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen? Why are we taught that<note place="margin">Gen. 3. Tit. 3. 13. Col 4. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>Tubulkan</hi> wrought cunninglie eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie craft of braſſe and of yron? that <hi>Iubal</hi> was a maker of tents, that <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> was a Carpenter, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles were fiſhers, that <hi>Peters</hi> hoſt was a Tanner, that <hi>Luke</hi> was a Phiſition, that <hi>Zeans</hi> was a Lawier, that <hi>Ioſeph, Moſes, Dauid,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were Magiſtrates, and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the people? The Scripture is ſhort and telleth vs in a word, that theſe all had a ſet calling wherein they exerciſed themſelues. This no doubt, as all other things was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for our learning: And what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing can wée learne thereby but to doe the like? what though a man maie recreate himſelfe ſometime, maie a man therefore doe nothing els? Doe not men make a God of plaie, when they knowe no other
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2469:38"/> pleaſure but it? If the morning be faire and calme, come ſaie they, heere is a goodlie morning to haue a game at boules in. If the weather be boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous, then it is a iollie cloſe daie, to haue a game at cardes in, no wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commeth amiſſe, faire or foule, they can paſſe awaie the time well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. If dinner bée once done, come then, what ſhall we doe? for the time they thinke is loſt that is not ſpent that waies. After ſupper they cannot ſléepe, except they firſt plaie a ſette at Mawe.</p>
                  <p>Thus when they are at plaie, then their minde is vpon their game, when they are from plaie, then muſt they tell what a game they loſt with dalieng too long, or for not croſſing a trumpe in their fellowes waie. Then muſt they that are preſent continue the talke, with telling the like lucke that they haue ſéene. If their ſport bée hawking, then muſt all their talke be of the faire flight they had. The like maie bée ſaid almoſt of all other games. So
<pb facs="tcp:2469:39"/> that, as you ſée, all their thoughts are taken vp of plaie. And what a miſerable life is this, that when there are ſo manie good things to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire after, yet that men ſhould chuſe to ſpende all their thoughtes vpon ſo vile and ſo baſe a thing as plaie is. I haue heard men ſpeake much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Atheiſtes, and Epicures, which thinking that there is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther life after this, imbrace and giue themſelues ouer to the delights of this preſent world: But if both their dooings were inquired after, I meruaile what difference a man could finde, betweene them and the gameſters of our time. They maie ſaie they looke for another life after this: but lette them ſhowe mée their faith by their déedes. No, no: if they thought not that the ſeconde comming of Chriſt to iudge both the quicke and the dead, were a tale of Robin hood, they would neuer doe as they doe. The rich reuenewes of Noble men and Gentlemen, are as it were the ſtore houſes of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2469:39"/> Lord, by theſe maiſter conductes, hée conuaieth foode and raiment, and other neceſſaries vnto euerie man. The Noble men therefore, which haue ſo great truſt committed vnto them, ought to liue carefullie and faithfullie in their calling: they ought to haue an eie to their offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, leaſt they abuſe their tenaunts: they ought to looke that nothing bée ſpent prodigallie, but to good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. Lette nothing bée loſt, ſaith<note place="margin">Iohn. 6.</note> Chriſt, for that is the beſt houſekée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping when all is done. Then ſhall they make men reuerence them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déede, when they thus ſhowe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues fathers and nurſes of whole countreies. I ſpeake of them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I am occaſioned by that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which I haue in hande: for their hands are chiefe in this treſpaſſe. They doe not onelie followe ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming themſelues, but they cauſe their whole traine to offende with them: And becauſe all men will willinglie followe the examples of the beſt, all the whole countreie al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt,
<pb facs="tcp:2469:40"/> by meanes of the outragious gaming of their ſuperiours, are brought to ſette their hearts vpon the like vanities. If they would conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der well of the matter, they might ſoone perceiue that they are placed in ſo high a calling, for a farre more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent purpoſe, for they are God his ſtewards, and ſhall no doubt giue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their ſtewarſhip. If all that which they poſſeſſe, were for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues alone, what good could come to the owners thereof, but the behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of it with their eies? The great maſſe of wealth therefore which they haue in their hands, is not for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues alone: but they haue the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of the matter onelie, and are to ſée that the Lord his prouiſion bée beſtowed, vpon his people.</p>
                  <p>If they were thus carefull in the Lords matters, and would not neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligentlie giue ouer this their charge vnto others, a great deale of their time which is now loſt in riot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous and ſuperfluous gaming ſhould bée verie well beſtowed, and to
<pb facs="tcp:2469:40"/> good purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>It is reported of my olde Lord of <hi>Oxford,</hi> that hée kept Lawi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in his houſe, which might iudge betwéene plea and plea, ano take vp the controuerſies which might fall out betwéene his tenaunts, or thoſe which were vnder his gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>If the Noble men in our daies would followe this worthie pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne, men ſhould not be hindered ſo in their calling with following Lawe matters, their eies ſhould not be ſo wearied with waiting and loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Tearme after Tearme for a daie of hearing.</p>
                  <p>If they would leaue of from following ſo gréedelie their paſtimes, and bend themſelues to ouerrule ſuch troubleſome fellowes, as without cauſe moleſt ſimple men. If they would deliuer the poore, the fatherleſſe, and ſuch as haue none to helpe them.</p>
                  <p>If they would, (as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith)<note place="margin">Iob. 29. 17.</note> breake the chawes of the vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous,
<pb facs="tcp:2469:41"/> and plucke the praie out of his téeth, I dare be bold to ſaie, that the tongues not onelie of thoſe that receiue benefite by this their honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable paines, but euen as manie as heard of it, would bleſſe them: the ſpending of a thouſand pound at a Chriſtmaſſe, will not doe them halfe the like honour. It is méete, I graunt, that in their diette, in their apparell, and in euerie parte of their ciuill behauiour, they ſhould haue ſome outward marke of eccel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie aboue the reſt: they maie hunt, they maie hawke, or vſe anie other kinde of moderate exerciſe: but the executing of Iuſtice and Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is the thing they are called vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and it is an honourable calling. This labouring in ſome honeſt cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, is ſo well pleaſing in the ſight of God, that beſide the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitte which commeth thereby, he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth men take great delight in it. You ſhall oftentimes heare one that goeth to cart, make a more chéere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſound with whiſtling, then anie
<pb facs="tcp:2469:41"/> idle fidler that goeth about the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie can do with his inſtrument. The Tailers, Schomakers, and other men of occupation, that ſing at their worke, how merrie are they? for their labour, by reaſon of the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent minding of that they goe about, is not perceiued of them. And when a man hath fullie purpoſed with himſelfe to do anie thing, hée doth it then chéerefullie without anie bui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, he ſetteth himſelfe to it, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth his minde therein. On the contrarie part, an idle bodie hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies a variable minde: Becauſe he is not throughlie perſwaded to goe through with anie thing, his minde cannot tell what to doe. The ſléepe ſaith <hi>Salomon,</hi> of him that trauaileth<note place="margin">Preacher. 5. 11.</note> is ſwéete, whether he eate little or much: but the ſacietie of the rich will not ſuffer him to ſléepe. The thing that deceiueth a great manie is this: they thinke, becauſe the matter, where about gameſters and labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring men buſie themſelues is all one, becauſe they both do perteine to this
<pb facs="tcp:2469:42"/> preſent life, they thinke it maketh no matter whether they followe labour or gaming, but they doe not conſider wiſelie of this thing. For labour is commaunded of God: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though labour in it ſelfe ſéeme to bée but a baſe thing, yet to obeie the voice of the great God is a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious matter. Beſide this, though wée inioie profite by our labour, yet our brother alſo is profited thereby: wée doe good to ſome, and harme to none. The like cannot be ſaide of vs, when we followe gaming, though we vſe no deceite in it: but if our labour be without deceite, it maie truelie be ſaid of vs. The moſt that can bée ſaid for games is, that wée maie vſe them, and it is alreadie graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that a moderate vſe of ſuch games as are lawfull, ought not to be condemned: but we haue no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement for them, as we haue for labouring in ſome honeſt calling. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other miſchifes that come by following plaie, this is not the leaſt that men thereby fall into euill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2469:42"/> euen amongſt ſuch as ſcoffe at all religion, and goodnes, which thing is of great force to driue vs from God. He that delighteth ſo much in plaie, he cannot alwaies haue his choice of companie, but for the moſt part is faine to take ſuch as come next hand, and therefore gameſters vſe ſuch places as are open &amp; common for euerie bodie. Though a man be neuer ſo wicked, yet if he be a gameſter, hée is a good fellow, vnleſſe he be a raſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, for that is ſome diſcredit to them. But otherwiſe though in the ſight of God he be as vile as anie lothſome begger that goeth from doore to doore, his companie is good. They neuer marke the common prouerbe, which béeing rife in euerie mans mouth, is noted of all men to bée true, that a ſcabbed ſhéepe infecteth the whole flocke. Knowe ye not ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, that a little leauen leaueneth a whole lumpe of dowe. And what is<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4. 6.</note> it but an intollerable pride, to thinke our ſelues ſo ſtrong, that no companie can infect vs? We maie, I graunt,
<pb facs="tcp:2469:43"/> haue to doe with the wicked, ſo farre foorth as we ſhall be conſtrained by the neceſſities of this preſent life: for otherwiſe we muſt goe out of the world, as the Apoſtle ſaith: but yet we muſt be no companions with<note place="margin">Ephe. 5. 7.</note> them. We maie, I graunt, haue an other purpoſe in kéeping companie then to be infected with them. But as one that walketh in the Sunne, ſhall be ſunburnt, though the end of his walking in it bée not to be ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burnt, ſo likewiſe will it bée with vs in kéeping companie with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Demas.</speaker>
                  <p>I but ſir you knowe we are all ſinners, whie then ſhould I auoide an other mans companie, when I am a ſinner as well as hée?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>Wée are all ſinners in déed but all men doe not make a ſport of ſinne, if there were no difference a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſinners, whie ſhould the holie Ghoſt forbidde the godlie to vſe the companie of the wicked?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Demas.</speaker>
                  <p>But how can I iudge, when a man is ſuch a ſinner as ought to be auoided.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:2469:43"/>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>The iudgement of this matter is eaſie inough. For though I be forbidden to eſpie a mote in my brothers eie, when I can well inough abide to haue a beame in mine owne eie. Though I muſt not iudge before the time, but thinke the beſt, ſo long as a thing maie be well taken: yet muſt I not be without all iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Though loue be not ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, yet it maketh not a man a foole. When I heare a man ſpew out blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, when I heare him talke fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thilie, when I heare him rage, ſhall I not iudge him to be a wicked man? Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>Abraham</hi> came into <hi>Gerar,</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the peoples conuerſation, he ſaid:<note place="margin">Gen. 20. 11.</note> ſurelie the feare of God is not in this place: yet wée muſt not accuſe him of raſh iudgement. O it were a fearfull thing: if the Lord when hée commeth, ſhould finde vs eating and drinking, with publicans &amp; ſinners. And whie ſhould a man be ſo grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>mpanie? for though they can be content to vſe the companie one of an other, and by kéeping com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie
<pb facs="tcp:2469:44"/> together, to paſſe awaie the time pleaſantlie. Yet, when the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie is broken vp, &amp; euerie man gone to his ſeuerall abiding place, If then anie thing ſhal be ſpoken in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of anie of their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panions, they cannot abide it: for by &amp; by they thinke they are diſpraiſed by it. They will then vſe ſuch woordes as tend to the abaſing one of an other, and what good fellowſhip call you that? But the loue of good men, though it bée vnperfect: yet it is in truth, the difference betwéene the euill and outward curteſie of worldlie men, and the Chriſtian vnitie of ſuch as feare God, is meruailous great. Who then would not rather wiſh to be of this companie? The world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings at their feaſting vſe curious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licates, They féede the eies of their geſſe with a great manie trimme things, to the ende they maie make report, that other men of their wealth, haue not the like furniture and prouiſion that they haue. But the children of God eate their meate
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2469:44"/> together with gladneſſe, and ſingle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart, without anie ſuch curioſitie. Whether a man be poore or rich, he is neither enuied nor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of them. The loue of <hi>Paule</hi> the Apoſtle, though he were an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent man, was yet meruailous great towards <hi>Oeneſimus</hi> béeing a ſeruaunt.</p>
                  <p>For he writeth thus, I beſéech thée for my ſonne <hi>Oeneſimus</hi> whom I haue begotten in my bondes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue him that is mine owne bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, receiue him as my ſelfe: If hée hath hurt thée, or oweth thée ought, that put on mine accounts: yea bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, let mée obtaine this pleaſure of thée in the Lorde, comfort my bowels in the Lord. The like abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce of more then motherlie affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion did the faithfull at <hi>Epheſus</hi> ſhew towardes the Apoſtle, béeing moſt ſorrie, becauſe he ſaide they ſhould ſée his face no more. Neither are they onelie tender harted to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the godlie, but euen towarde the wicked. The wicked Iewes
<pb facs="tcp:2469:45"/> perſecuted <hi>Hieremie</hi> for diſcouering their ſins, but when the iudgements of God were vpon them, his eies caſt foorth teares and ceaſed not. Men of the world will be ſorie, when they haue loſt a dailie friend, or a merrie companion: but the children of God are ſorie without anie ſuch reſpect. When wicked <hi>Abſolon</hi> a falſe trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, and an open rebell againſt his father, was taken away by death: yet the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> could not but be moued, He went vp to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ouer the gate and wept: and as he went, thus he ſaid, O my ſonne <hi>Abſolon,</hi> my ſonne, my ſonne <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> would God I had died for thée, O <hi>Abſolon</hi> my ſonne, my ſonne. Who would not wiſh to be amongſt this louing companie, whoſe talke is, how they might obeie the voice of the great God, when other talke of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles? They ſing Pſalmes &amp; hymnes together to the Lord, for all his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſheweth vnto the children of men. The godlie are readie euen with chéerfulneſſe, to do a man good:
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2469:45"/> But the wicked will not be at lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, euerie little thing will be an<note place="margin">Pro. 12 10.</note> hinderaunce in the matter, ſo that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen their mercies are cruell. Whie then ſhould a man be ſo gréedie of their acquaintance? Whie ſhould a man forſake an honeſt calling, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe their fancies? And whie are we ſo fond of theſe worldlie delights? Are they not common to vs with all Turkes and Infidels? Is not the Turke better able to haue all kinde of glorious triumphes, then anie of vs? Maie he not haue what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is pleaſant to his eie, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightſome to his taſt? Maie hée not haue whatſoeuer in this world his heart can deſire? Hath not the beaſt of the fielde pleaſure in eating, in drinking, in ſléeping? Doe not the birdes ſport themſelues with ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing among the gréene braunches? Doe not the young bullockes ſkippe and leape in the gréene meddowes? naie, do not the beaſts of the field go beyond vs in this thing? Doth not the hawke take a greater delight in
<pb facs="tcp:2469:46"/> following hir praie, then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fawkners doe in looking on? doth not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hound or the ſpaniell take delight in an higher kinde, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hope of obteining their praie, then the hunters do in hearing or beholding the ſport a far of? Whie then are we ſo gréedie of gaming.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Demas.</speaker>
                  <p>This your treatiſe of continuance at gaming, hath ben ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, &amp; therfore, for memories ſake, I praie you gather your reaſons that you haue vſed into a narrowe roome, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> I maie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better carrie them away. <hi>Paule.</hi> The ſum of that which I haue ſaid in this treatiſe, is this: ſéeing eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie man without exception, muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt part of his life in ſome certeine &amp; dailie calling: ſéeing conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance at plaie cannot be mainteined without infinit charges, which ought rather to be beſtowed vpon ſuch as haue néed: ſéeing the Lord hath ioined an honeſt delight, to a dailie calling, which continuance at gaming doth want: ſeing by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce at gaming, men muſt of neceſſitie fall into euill co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie, which is of gret force to driue
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2469:46"/> vs from God: ſéeing by this meanes we bar our ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> louing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godlie: ſéeing by following our dailie calling, we obeie the voice of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great God, &amp; do ſome good to our brethren, which cannot be done with continuall gaming: laſt of all, ſéeing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> delight y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue in gaming is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to vs with all Turks &amp; Infidels &amp; with the beaſts of the field, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no man muſt follow gaming.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>Of daunſing. The fourth Chapter.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DEmas.</speaker>
                  <p>You diuided games into ſuch, wherin men are the chife do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: &amp; into ſuch, wherein they are the lookers on You haue ſpoken of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt kinde, though in few words, yet in as manie as I deſire: I praie you ſpeake now of the other kinde, of this kind is daunſing: what thinke you of it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Peter Marter</hi> vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Iudges, ſpeaketh of manie kindes of daunces. But if you ſpeake of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> kinde of dauncing, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is receiued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs in euerie place, wher dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſing is vſed, all good conſciences muſt néedes
<pb facs="tcp:2469:47"/> condemne it. For, is it a ſeemelie thing (thinke you) that a Chriſtian man, or a Chriſtian woman ſhould be ſo much delighted with hearing a prophane, and ſometimes a filthie ſong plaide vppon an inſtrument, that they ſhould leape for ioie at the hearing of it? Shall the Lord thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der out his terrible iudgements a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſtinking ſinne of adulterie, and ſhall we holde it lawfull to laie baites and allurements to intrappe our ſelues therein? In the long pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that is vſed in maſ king, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene daunce and daunce, doe they not vſe all kinde of filthie talke that they can deuiſe? In other kindes of daunſing where they doe not vſe to talke together, what wanton ieſtures are vſed? The young man muſt ſhew himſelfe as youthfull as maie bée, his turning on the toe, his capering, and all his other trickes want their grace, if they bée not done in the ſight of his ladie. The woman muſt ſet out hir bodie, and minſe it farre vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéemelie, either for the baſhfull mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2469:47"/> of a virgin, or the chaſt behauiour of a married woman. A man maie ſuppoſe in déede that fire and flaxe maie be together without anie daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: But what a ſtraunge fondneſſe is this? Wée condemne the popiſh Phareſies of intollerable pride, for lifting vp the power of man, and for ſaieng that they are able to keepe themſelues from anie ſinne: And yet we thinke our ſelues ſo ſtrong, that we maie delight our eies with ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vpon anie woman, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we maie beholde anie kinde of wanton looke, or light ieſture whatſoeuer, without anie harme done: or anie wicked thought, ſo much as once conceiued thereby, either of the dauncers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lookers on. If we thought not our ſelues ſo ſtrong, whie would we ſuffer ſuch prouocations which are as bellowes, to inflame the hearts of young men, and to ſet on fire the heartes of young women towardes them againe. He that loueth daunger muſt néeds fall into it. And the diuell knoweth that temptations come no
<pb facs="tcp:2469:48"/> waie ſo forceablie to our fancie, as by the eieſight: And therefore he did not tempt Chriſt, by deſcribing vnto him in manie wordes the glorie of the world: but he taketh him vp on high, and ſheweth it him: he knew<note place="margin">Math. 4.</note> that this was the better waie. The courtier confeſſeth that a wanton loke is of greater force to inge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thilie luſt, which he calleth loue, then a thouſand words. The godlie man Iob, knowing the weakneſſe of man, how great it was, had alwaies a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſuſpition of himſelfe, and was ſo farre from vſing trifling wordes, or light geſtures towards anie woman: that hée made a couenant with his<note place="margin">Iob. 31.</note> eies, leaſt by looking wiſtlie vppon hir, he ſhould thinke on a maide. How dare anie of vs then giue ouer our ſelues to daunſing, where ſuch light geſtures are not onelie vſed, but alſo openlie profeſſed. Howe<note place="margin">Eſaie. 3. 16.</note> can wée beholde the ſtretched out neckes, and the wandering eies: but that (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith) wée ſhall bée in as great daunger, as
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2469:48"/> one that ſléepeth in the middeſt of the ſea, and as he that ſléepeth in the top of a maſt? And yet hée that ſhall finde fault with vs for it, is a new fangled fellowe, &amp; nothing can pleaſe<note place="margin">Pro. 23. 34.</note> him. In other thinges we will eaſilie graunt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> force of temptations by our eie-ſight: ſée for your loue (ſaie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunts) and bye for your moneie. They knowe by looking vpon their wares, we are ſooner brought to bye them: and therefore the thriftie huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band giueth counſell to kéepe purſe at market, onelie in this thing we will acknowledge no ſuch matter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Demas.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet we read, that godlie women haue daunced: And <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Exo. 15. 20.</note> a man according to God his owne heart did daunce.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>The modeſt and ſober daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that godlie women vſed, a part by themſelues after ſome notable vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, to giue thanks therefore, ought to be no cloke for our wanton daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. For we count it no ſport, except men &amp; women daunce together: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is eaſilie perceiued the filthy ende
<pb facs="tcp:2469:49"/> of our dauncing. <hi>Dauid</hi> daunced in déede, but is his dauncing and ours anie thing like? <hi>Dauid</hi> lift vs his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and daunced before the Arke: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, béeing a ſigne of the fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble preſence of God, it was brought home from the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> vnto the people of God againe. But marke (I praie you) what the text ſaith: <hi>Michol</hi> ſawe his dauncing, and mocked him: belike it was no courtlie daunce, for then it ſhould haue pleaſed hir well inough. And <hi>Dauid</hi> aunſwering hir<note place="margin">1. Sam 6.</note> mockes, ſaith: I will be yet more vile then thus, and will be lowe in mine owne ſight. We vſe to braue it, and to ſhewe our ſelues as gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant as maie be in our dauncing: But <hi>Dauid</hi> abaſed himſelfe in his dauncing, and for this cauſe was he contentemned of <hi>Michol.</hi> He choſe no wanton Dame to daunce with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, neither daunced hée after a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie vaine Heatheniſh ſong: but after a Pſalme of thankeſgiuing. Neuer compare <hi>Dauid</hi> his daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with ours, for there is no
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2469:49"/> more likelihood betwéene them, then is betwéene heauen and hell. <hi>Dauid</hi> cauſed not ſo manie inſtruments to be made to ſerue God his glorie, as we doe to ſerue our wanton luſts: as the prophet <hi>Amos</hi> telleth vs. So that, if we will haue our daunſing appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of the Lord, we muſt vſe ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kinde. For I dare boldlie ſaie, vpon my reaſons alleadged, the word of God is my warrant, that the daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing we now vſe, is abhominable. Thoſe that are deſirons to heare more of this matter, maie read a learned treatiſe written in French, and dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated by the French Miniſters of the reformed Churches, vnto the king of <hi>Nauarre:</hi> the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereof is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt our fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie kinde of daunſing.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2469:50"/>
               <head>Of Dice and Card-plaie. Chap. 5.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DEmas.</speaker>
                  <p>You haue prooued that we offend in daunſing, not onelie as we doe in hunting and hawking, by vſing of it too much: but that we offend, if we vſe our wanton kinde of daunſing at all. Ther be other things, wherein I would gladlie haue your iudgement: but that I am afraid I haue troubled you too long alreadie. I told you when I came, I would make you wearie of me before I went, and I am afraid I haue bene as good as my word.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>Naie trulie ſir, you doe not trouble me, and therefore I praie you doe not thinke ſo: we méete (you knowe) but ſeldome, and therefore I wold be loth to part from you ſo ſoone.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Demas.</speaker>
                  <p>Séeing you will néedes haue mée trouble you, I will goe forward with that which I was about to ſpeak. Among all games that are vſed, Dice and Cardplaie are worſe reported of, then anie other
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2469:50"/> kinde of game: and yet is no other of game vſed halfe ſo much. Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gameſters themſelues for vſing this game, are much to blame: or els thoſe that giue it ſo euill a report, I praie ſir, how thinke you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>I will tell you <hi>Demas,</hi> if we will well marke the riotous and outragious dice, and card-plaie, that hath ſpread it ſElfe, and now ouerflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth euerie part of the land: If (I ſaie) we ſhal way with our ſelues vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, the innumerable ſleights and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoods that are incident to gaming, &amp; the infinite miſchiefes that haue come thereby, both to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of God, &amp; alſo to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> common wealth: we ſhall not one whit meruaile, if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godlie ſorrow that a Chriſtian heart conceiueth thereby, makes him euen to crie out vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The diuel indéed doth couer his crafts in all occupations: but he is nener lightlie ſo ſuttle, but that the chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, in vſing thoſe things they haue bought, euermore lightlie ſpie him out: Onelie in this kinde of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe hée doeth excell, hée hath
<pb facs="tcp:2469:51"/> ſhewed héere what he can doe. A man ſhall be deceiued, yet can hée neuer lightlie tell who hath hurt him. The Cards muſt be clipt for ſome kind of games at the toppes, for ſome other at the ſides. When it commeth to a mans courſe to deale, he hath taught vs how to packe: when another dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, he hath taught vs how to deceiue by cutting. If more plaie then two, then commeth in couſoning: two muſt deceiue the third, or thrée the fourth. If the fillie ſoule begin to be wearie of this paſtime, becauſe it is to dull a game, &amp; had rather heare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ratling of the Dice: or if chaunging the game, he hopeth to change his lucke: they are then alſo redie for him. Their dice are redie ground or ſtopt: They haue high men, they haue lowe men, they haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ard cater traies. So that whether he be diſpoſed to plaie at Hazard, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero, Nouem, Paſſage, Ticke tacke, Iriſh, what game ſoeuer he chooſeth, they are with him to bring. I will not take vpon me to tell all. For thoſe that haue practiſed gaming of a long
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2469:51"/> time, and haue bene at it earlie and late. Thoſe that haue inquired after the ſleights thereof, and haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailouſlie profited that waies, are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes to ſéeke, and ſometimes alſo ouertaken thereby.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Demas.</speaker>
                  <p>I but ſir, doe you not perceiue, that theſe are the faultes of thoſe that abuſe the ſport: and not of gaming it ſelfe. There is deceipt v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in euerie occupation, there is craft (as they ſaie) in dawbing: will you therefore condemne all occupations. <hi>Paule.</hi> The craft that is vſed in oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupations, is in the perſons, &amp; not in the thing it ſelfe: but you cannot ſaie ſo of Diceplaie. In euerie trade, there is ſome honeſt ende: for they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments and conducts (as it were) to ſerue the prouidence of God, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the maintenaunce of our life, and defence of our bodie: They tend (I ſaie) to the maintenaunce one of another: But gaming hath a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ende. It doth not yéeld anie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie to his brother for the moneie it receiueth, but they ſtake downe
<pb facs="tcp:2469:52"/> their monie then muſt it be yours or mine, win it and take it. A great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie men thinke, becauſe it is not ſaid in preciſe and expreſſe words, that the Lord will haue no man plaie for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neie, that therefore there is no Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture againſt it. Theſe men ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider in like manner, that it is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the Scriptures, that there be thrée perſons in the Godhead, that Chriſt is both God and man, that our infants ought to be baptiſed: yet none of vs doubteth, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe things are ſet down as certeinlie, as if they were in moſt plaine words expreſſed: ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe is it with the thing I haue now in hand. The holie ghoſt ſetting down the propertie of loue, telleth vs that<note place="margin">Cor. 13. 5.</note> it is ſo deſirous to pleaſure the partie it loueth, that oftentimes it ſéeketh not his owne. If to hazard our monie to put in daunger the moneie of our brother, be not flat contrarie to this propertie of loue, I knowe not what is contrarie. All baſe golde, and cract ſiluer is currant monie: belike they thinke it is good enough for the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:2469:52"/> wares they vtter. So that, to ſet the faults that I ſpake of before aſide, you ſée gaming it ſelfe hath no good ende. But (I praie you) tell me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you ſaie theſe be the faults of men, and not of the thing: where doe you knowe anie, if hée hath bene a gameſter of anie long time, but that hée hath béene infected with theſe ſleights? Are not theſe woords v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall amongſt gameſters: At cardes I will deceiue mine owne Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if I can: At Dice I will not truſt mine owne brother.</p>
                  <p>They knowe that the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of a praie, is able to make halfe an honeſt man a thiefe. Becauſe therefore this kinde of plaie miniſtreth ſuch opportunitie to deceiue, they will not truſt a gameſter though otherwiſe hée bée a reaſonable honeſt man.</p>
                  <p>I haue bene a gameſter my ſelfe a great while too long, and I haue marked ſome men of all degrées, both high and lowe, howe they haue behaued them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb facs="tcp:2469:53"/> at plaie: yet can I not ſaie, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of my ſelfe, or of anie that I haue ſeene, (and yet I haue ſéene a great manie) that they haue bene free from winking, croſſe, diſcarding, or from ſome deceipt or other, &amp; indéed, to ſaie the truth, this kind of game is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els, but a profeſſion how to deceiue cunninglie. I doe not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſpeake what I my ſelfe haue ſéene: for manie that haue bene game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of a long time, and haue refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med this their corruption, will wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with me, that that which I haue ſaid is true. <hi>Paſchaſius Ecloulenſis,</hi> a Doctor of Phiſicke, béeing a tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailer in <hi>Spaine,</hi> for manie yeares, was a daily beholder of courtly game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and others. (He beeing a tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailer, marked things more narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was the ende of his trauell, and we are all giuen to marke things more neerelie in a ſtrange place, then at home.) This <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> that I ſpeake of, ſaith plainlie of all game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, Noble men and others, that there is none but hée will deceiue if
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2469:53"/> he can. For though manie care not greatlie for the moneie, yet becauſe they diſdaine to léeſe, and the victorie is ſomwhat, they will not ſtick to help themſelues as much as maie be. This is their order. Young gameſters, by reaſon of their vnſkilfulneſſe, or els for that they are ſo ſharpe ſette, that they can not match themſelues, but with diſaduauntage, alwaies goe by the worſt. And when they haue bene bitten of a long time, thoſe that haue couſoned him, will make him ſome part of amends, with making of him priuie to his ſleights, that they maie praie vpon young nouiſes, as they before were a praie to others. Men are ſoone brought to this lure. For what gameſter holdeth it vnlawfull, to get againe by the ſame meanes, all that which they loſt to others before? Nay, though at their firſt ſitting to plaie, they meane honeſtlie, &amp; purpoſe to plaie no otherwiſe then the cards ſerue: yet if they be much in loſſe, they thinke it a meruailous follie, by ſome knacke or other, not to ſéeke to
<pb facs="tcp:2469:54"/> recouer themſelues againe. So that a man can hardlie truſt, not onelie ſhifters, which liue by plaie: but euen ciuill gameſters: thoſe which pretend no other ende of plaie then good fellowſhip. And I praie you doe not their owne conſcience tell them, that the winnings that come by play, are vnlawfull? For if one oweth them monie that waies, they make no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of it, but as of deſperate debt, though the partie that oweth it them, be a man able enough: and to take vp a mans ſtake, when it is loſt, is yet accounted fairer plaie. I appeale to the conſciences of all thoſe that vſe this kinde of game, whether y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> things that I ſaie of them be true, or no. And if they be true, I aſke them, with what face they can defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Demas.</speaker>
                  <p>I but ſir, I praie you let vs reſon of the matter, before you come to giue ſentence. Indéed (as you ſaie) though ſome gameſters ſaie they can plaie without deceipt: yet I think it is but Hypocriſie in them. For,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2469:54"/> though they can bée content to vſe ſquare plaie, ſo long as the Cardes goe on their ſide, (for they can but winne, though they ſhoulde vſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt) yet when lucke (as they call it) goeth againſt them, they will bée ſure to ſaue themſelues from looſing: ſo that the partie with whome they plaie, ſhall bée ſure to goe by the woorſt. But you knowe, many times the parties that plaie are cunning all alike: for gaming hath no ſuch wit in it, but that it maie eaſilie be found out, if men would bend themſelues to it.</p>
                  <p>There is nothing then that bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the ſwaie, but the chaunce (as they tearme it) of the Dice: for one winneth one daie, and another an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other daie: They winne (I ſaie) and looſe by courſe, as it falleth out. What then (thinke you,) is the thing that mooueth men to plaie, when they haue no aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of him, with whome they plaie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paul.</speaker>
                  <p>The thing that moueth men to
<pb facs="tcp:2469:55"/> plaie, when they cannot deceiue, though they would, I thinke is an ouer well conceiuing of themſelues. For, though they ſée no reaſon why, yet becauſe they like better of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, then of the partie with whom they plaie, they thinke the Dice muſt néedes goe on their ſides: for they ſuppoſe that the victorie ſhall alwaies be beſtowed vpon the worthier per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Why (ſaie they) ſhould not I win as well as he?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Demas.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, but though men doe léeſe at this lotting, and ſquare plaie at Dice and Cardes, yet will they continue plaie ſtill: what thinke you is the cauſe of this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>Euen the ſame pride that before I ſpake of, and therefore the partie that loſeth, calleth the victorie of him, with whom he doth play, <hi>Nid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gits lucke.</hi> He ſéeth no wittie indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of the conquerour, which might driue him to confeſſe, that the partie with whom he plaieth is too hard for him: and being ſtill the worthier per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in his owne conceipt, he think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:2469:55"/> that at the laſt the Dice will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member him, ſo they neuer make an end of plaie. If therefore we looke vpon the firſt cauſe that moueth men to plaie at this game, we muſt néedes miſlike of it. Now, if we looke vppon the matter wherevpon this game doth conſiſt, and without the which it will not be, we ſhall ſée it is monie. For they hope to winne, or els why ſhould they plaie? and you knowe that hope is couetous.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Demas.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, but I cannot ſo ſoone yéeld vnto you in this matter. For manie rich merchants, and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen doe vſe this kinde of ſport, which I thinke make no great ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of moneie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſpeake, as if rich men were not couetous. Doeth not the Poet ſaie, and doth not dailie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience teach vs, that <hi>Creſcit amor nummi, quantùm ipſa pecunia creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit?</hi> It is a popiſh preſumption to thinke, that we are not prone to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous deſires, as we are to all other ſinnes. But plaieng at this moneie
<pb facs="tcp:2469:56"/> game, doth allure vs to this ſin, which thing we haue little néed of. &amp; therfore it is the will of God that we ſhould auoid ſuch allurements.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Demas.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet gameſters, of all other men are commonlie franke fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes: and therefore of all ſinnes, I cannot ſée, how you can charge them with the ſinne of couetouſneſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>They are franke indéede, when at their hoſts, or at a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans houſe the paie the boxe, or giue to anie that ſtand by, or ſpend it in good chéere, but their franknes comes alwaies out of another mans purſe: ſo that they are couetous, but yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a more gentlemanlie manner, then the miſerlie people in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie are You maie call it, a ſtatelie &amp; a loftie kinde of couetouſneſſe: yet (as you ſaie,) there is a kinde of riot ioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with it: for they hazard their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, to ſatiſfie their affections. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you are ſomewhat doubtfull in this point, I wil proue vnto you by a viſible demonſtration, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all gamſters are couetous. All gameſters, though
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:2469:56"/> they had rather plaie ſmall game, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſit out: yet if they haue vſed franke plaie, and are driuen either for want of moneie, or els for that the partie that plaieth with them will not ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture much moneie, if they be thus driuen to plaie for a ſmall ſum, they plaie not with halfe the delight they were accuſtomed to plaie with all: neither care they to plaie with him whom they loue déerelie. By y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which things it is euident, that there ſport is to win moneie. Thus, whether you looke to the firſt cauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moueth men to this game, or to the matter wherv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon it doeth conſiſt, wée ſée it cannot be allowed of. And if we looke vppon the formall cauſe. If (I ſaie) we will looke vpon the forme &amp; faſhion of the game it ſelfe, wee ſhall finde, that it deſerueth as little fauour as the other two cauſes that are alreadie ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of. If one bée ouerſéene at Mawe, and againſt his will looſe his dealing, ſhall he not looſe foure? At Ticke tacke if a man touch the wrong chip, doth he not looſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> game.
<pb facs="tcp:2469:57"/> The like maie be ſaid of the reſt: for what fairer plaie then dotage. But in bargaining if the like aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage be taken, though the common Lawe alloweth it, yet our Lawe of conſcience doth ouerrule the matter. And who is he that will not crie out vpon a man, &amp; giue his friends war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of him, if taketh vauntage of an Obligation, when by forgetting the day, the monie is brought a daie after the date? And yet who ſéeth not that there is the like equitie in both? For if they ſaie that the partie that is ouerſéene, and of whom the vauntage is taken, did agrée vpon the matter, at their ſitting to plaie, &amp; that he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth well enough that it is the order of plaie, and that it is lawfull for him that is ouertaken, to take the like ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntage of him that hath the forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: euerie man knoweth that a man maie as trulie ſaie the ſame of the forfeiture of an obligation. If an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere be made, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the one is a ſerious matter, &amp; the other is done in ſport: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of God, which is a touchſtone to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:2469:57"/> trie euerie déede, euerie word, euerie thought. This word of God allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no ſuch diſtinction, ſinne is ſinne, whether it be committed in earneſt or in ſport. Take héede of this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, if you will, for it is the méere ſophiſtrie of Sathan. And (I praie you) what occaſion of wrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is giuen, euen by gaming it ſelf? If a die ſtand a wrie at the fall, how manie gameſters can tell whether the faireſt to the caſter, or the faireſt to the ſkie ſhould be the throwe. At Mawe, if the ace of hearts be turned vp, when he that is to make, maketh this for it, then doth a meruailous controuerſie ariſe, whether he that turneth it vp ſhould win the ſet, or he that winneth fiue tricks: then muſt wagers be laide. I remember once there aroſe ſuch heart-burning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene two, for the like blinde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie, that béeing dailie compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons before, they met not together, of a quarter of a yeare after. They had both likelie games, the one aſketh a card, an other for me (ſaith the other:)
<pb facs="tcp:2469:58"/> thus they both aſked ſo long, till the whole bunch was out. The queſtion was, whether the trumpe that was turned vp at the laſt, ſhould be a voide card, or no. The diuell hath intangled euerie game with the like doubts, and we carrie a waiward na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture about with vs that will ſoone be prouoked, &amp; harme néeds little helpe, and thus much for the formal cauſe, and for the game it ſelfe. Now, if we ſhall come to the end wherefore this game is vſed, we ſhall alſo finde ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient matter to condemne it, the end that is pretended, is a recreation, let vs therefore conſider, whether it be ſo or no. Euerie recreation doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh &amp; quicken our ſpirits, but Dice and card plaie is ſo quiet, &amp; ſo drou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie a paſtime, that if the deſire of win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning did not kéepe them awake, the gameſters would be oftentimes rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to fall a ſléepe. I will not ſaie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, but ſome one that vſeth to plaie for moneie, maie be earneſt at plaie ſometimes, though he plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for niflles: but the cauſe of this
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:2469:58"/> his delight, is the calling to minde of his former ſport: or els to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the cunninger to winne his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers moneie the next time that hée plaieth. But if it were agréed vpon, that all plaie for moneie ſhould ceaſe: In a ſhort time men would haue as much delight to looke vpon a ſpade or a clubbe, or to turne one chip out of one table into an other, as they haue now in péeling of ſtrawes. It is not ſo in ſhooting. It is not ſo in tenniſſe plaie, in running, in ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, in throwing the barre, or the hammer. It is not ſo in games that aſke the exerciſe of the bodie. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member maiſter <hi>Aſcham</hi> hath a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie<note place="margin">In his booke of shooting.</note> ſimilitude againſt ſuch deceiuing paſtimes. We doe not vſe (ſaith he) to whette our knife vpon a chalke ſtone, for that would not ſharpen it, but make it more blunt: neither (ſaie I) if we wuld refreſh our wits, are we to goe to a paire of cards, for they will not quicken, but dull them, It is not ſo with ſhooting. It is not ſo with anie manlie kinde of
<pb facs="tcp:2469:59"/> exerciſe, for they ſtirre vp a certeine liuelineſſe in a man. Thereby hée is made quicke and readie to take in hand anie commendable thing: ſo that the abuſe of plaieng for monie béeing taken awaie, there maie bée a verie good vſe of them: neither can thoſe whoſe labour doth conſiſt in the exerciſe of the minde be well with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Demas.</speaker>
                  <p>Your mentioning of ſhooting hath brought to my minde a reaſon againſt a great deale of that, which you haue ſaid. For ſhooting (as you your ſelfe graunt) is a commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thing, and if it be not continued, England ſhall be bereft of a notable help againſt the time of warre. But how can it be mainteined, except men plaie for moneie?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>I am not againſt it, that ſhooting ſhould be mainteined: but the meanes whereby you woulde haue it mainteined, is a chargeable meanes, and would ſkant quite coſt. For though the common wealth bée helped by the thing it ſelf, in the time
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2469:59"/> of warre: yet the meanes that you ſpeake of, will helpe to pull it downe in the time of peace. Beſide this, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſkill, and ſtrength to vſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie weapon, hath his force from the bleſſing of the Lord. How can wée looke that the Lord will bleſſe this ſkill: when the meanes whereby we attaine thereto are not allowed of him? Thankes be to God, there bée meanes enough to traine vp a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient number that waies, though the ventering of our moneie to get our brothers moneie from him be laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide. But whie do you ſpeake ſo much of continuing anie ſport? Knowe you not that when men continue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie long time at plaie, that it is no longer a recreation, but a labour? When men vpon pleaſure will rowe vpon the Thames, after ſupper, in Summer time, we call it a recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but we doe not vſe to call it a recreation in the botemen, whoſe dailie labour doth conſiſt in rowing. Whereby it is eaſie to ſée, that the difference betwéene a recreation and
<pb facs="tcp:2469:60"/> a labour, doth conſiſt in the ſhortneſſe or length of time y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we beſtowe vpon either of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And amongſt other miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chifes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> come by plaieng for moneie, this is not the leaſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by this meanes they are held to long at plaie. For when a man looſeth, it is neuer light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſéene that he will giue ouer: and he that winneth ſhall be accounted a foule gameſter, if he leaue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other in the lurch. So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beſide y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loſſe of time, which might otherwiſe haue ben bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpent, they are oftentimes a tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. It is ſtrange to ſée, what ſodeine alteraions there ariſe in their outward lookes. If the cards go againſt them, then is there biting of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lip: but if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cards alter their courſe, then is ther clapping a taffaties, and giue me a hand, ther is (I ſaie) then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vncomelie ieaſting that the Apoſtle ſpeaketh againſt, which is vaine and<note place="margin">Ephe. 5. 4.</note> vnſauourie, but what doe I ſpeake of outward lookes? There is wr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ught through feare &amp; hope, a confuſion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole nature of man, you ſhall heare them oftentimes complaine, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:2469:60"/> backe akes with ſtooping, &amp; that their legs are benummed, their heads are pauled, &amp; their whole bodie is diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered: and yet this game muſt ſtill be accounted a recreation. Is not x. or a .xi. a clocke at night a fitte time (thinke you) to vſe recreations? And yet is this dark time of the night, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to this worke of darkneſſe, which they call a recreation: neither are they troubleſom to themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole houſe wher they plaie, &amp; to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole houſes where they dwel. They turne the day into night, as the Prophet ſaith: they turne top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie turnie, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole order of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord hath made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day for labour, &amp; the night for ſléepe: but they watch in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> night, &amp; ſléepe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daie. Thus if we looke into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> firſt moueth them to lot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, or ſquare play, it is pride: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce of it is a moneie matter, the forme &amp; faſhion of it is to take adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of our brothers ouerſight, and to miniſter occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of wra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gling: wherto may be added an inuincible argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,
<pb facs="tcp:2469:61"/> which now commeth to my minde. All the games at dice and cardes ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther goe by ſkill, or by méere lotte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. If they goe by ſkill, then is it a ſhame, that our ſkill that ſhould be for the benefite of our borther, ſhould turne to his hinderaunce: But if that goe by lotterie, it is againſt the third commaundement.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Demas.</speaker>
                  <p>Truelie ſir, I do not well vnderſtand your reaſon. I knowe (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déed) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our ſkill muſt not hinder our brother: for not onelie the lawe of God, but the lawe of nature, and of all nations is againſt it: but that which you ſpeake of the third com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, I cannot tell what it meaneth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>We are there commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, not to take the name of God in vaine. You knowe what a name is. A name is a thing, whereby anie thing is knowne. <hi>Salomon</hi> is knowne by his wiſdome. And if I ſaie the wiſe man ſaith ſo, you can tell whome I meane. So likewiſe is the prouidence of God, the name of God: it is a
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:2469:61"/> thing whereby he is knowne. Now, if I call for his name to witneſſe a trifle, what do I but take it in vaine? When I muſt néeds haue a ſpeciall determination immediatlie from the prouidence of God, whether a teſtar or a ſhilling ſhall be yours or mine, what doe I but make a mocke of his wiſdome, which diſtributeth to euerie man as it ſéemeth beſt vnto him? What dalieng is this with him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Demas.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet we reade, that <hi>Ioſua</hi> diuided their land to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> by lot.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>I doe not condemne all ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of lots, no more then I doe all kinde of ſwearing: but to vſe anie of them both, when there is no néede, muſt néeds be condemned. I thinke it were verie good, if all our demurs<note place="margin">Pro. 18. 18.</note> were ended by lot: for when the Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſtand at a ſtaie, &amp; cannot, or will not make an end of a matter, when a matter cannot be ended by anie or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie lawfull meanes, what ſhould men pauſe &amp; ſpend their money to no purpoſe? In ſuch a caſe (I graunt) we
<pb facs="tcp:2469:62"/> might haue a verie good vſe of ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of lots: but what maketh this for our common kinds of lotting? <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſua</hi> (you ſaie) did caſt lots. The land of <hi>Canaan</hi> was to be diuided among the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> to euerie Tribe a por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: now, becauſe there could be no ſuch equall diuiſion, but that there muſt néedes be ſome oddes in their portions, it was wiſdome both to put bye all ſuſpition of partialitie from <hi>Ioſua,</hi> and enuie from amongſt the people. It was wiſedome (I ſaie) for theſe cauſes to determine by lottes, what ſeuerall portion that ſhould be, that euerie ſeuerall Tribe ſhould haue. But we, when we haue mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie in our purſes, caſt lottes whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that which we haue ſhould bée none of ours, or whether we ſhal haue more to it. You ſée there is great ods betwéene theſe two. Othes and lots are to end controuerſies, and not to waite vpon our fancies. So that, to come againe to that which I was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to ſaie, the efficient and natural cauſe of this plaie, is pride &amp; couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:2469:62"/> In the forme is hard dealing, occaſion of falling out &amp; breach of the third commandement. The end is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempering of ſoule &amp; bodie, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer you haue reſpect vnto in this game, it is naught. Men wil not ſticke to think y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they haue meruailous hold of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, when they begin to play, they will ſet downe a quiet kinde of plaie, how much they will plaie for, and they will make an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd at a verie good time: but when the affection is once vp, all theſe thinges are cleane forgotten. Naie, though one hauing more care of his health, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an other, maketh mention of ending plaie: yet if an old fellow come out w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a wooden ieſt, and ſaith that is but a fooliſh cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome to go to bed a nights, this woo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ieſt ſhall be of force to kéepe them vp all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> night long. Trulie it is a wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull thing, &amp; almoſt vncredible, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is ſo manifeſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men ſhould take ſuch delight in hurting of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. Their ordinarie plaie delighteth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther is a meting pitched, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they make a daie of it (as they ſaie)
<pb facs="tcp:2469:63"/> and ſit by it, that is accounted a game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters feaſt: they are troubled then with ſurfetting more then they were accuſtomed, they make themſelues dronken with it, and yet they take ſuch delight in this goſſopping ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, that you ſhall haue there talke of it a great while after. All other delights are nothing, where this ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming is awaie. For as it is with a man that hath a bile vppon him, as then all the other parts of the bodie ſéeme to be without féeling: ſo other honeſt delights ſéeme to be nothing, in reſpect of that. Though they bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe that loue them, yet if they be no gameſters, they are not in the right crue, they are not (they thinke) where they ſhould be. Naie, this their itching deſire is of ſuch power, that though (by reaſon of their loſſes &amp; ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fettings) they for the time are wearie of it, though they make a vow, &amp; ſhall forfet monie when ſoeuer they turne to their vomit again: yet cannot theſe bars hold them from plaie, for their deſire in déede is vnnaturall. I haue
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2469:63"/> heard &amp; ſéene men caſting their peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worths, how they might make this kinde of game a recreation, &amp; not a toiling. I haue heard (I ſaie) that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, euen thoſe that were thought to haue more holde of themſelues then a great manie other haue deuiſed to bring this thing to paſſe: but it could neuer be. For as <hi>Parmeno</hi> ſaith in an other matter, <hi>Incerta haec ſi tu poſtules, ratione certa facere nihilo plus agas, quam ſi des operam, vt cum ratione inſanias.</hi> Thus haue I, as wel as it hath pleaſed God to make mée able, vnfolded and laid open the vgli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this beaſtlie game, to the end that gameſters ſéeing what a miſhape<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thing it is, might turne their loue from it, to a better thing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Demas.</speaker>
                  <p>You haue proued that dice and card plaie are, no recreations, as they are pretended: but you haue not yet ſpoken of the miſchiefs that come of them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>Their miſchiefes in déed are infinit, and to ſpeake in a word, they bréede contempt of all religion and
<pb facs="tcp:2469:64"/> goodneſſe. For what gameſter ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth anie account of religion? What gameſter will hazard the loſſe of a friend, or the loſſe of anie worldlie comfort, for the honour of his God? Naie, a man muſt be conformable, &amp; applie himſelfe to euerie companie, or els he is no méete man to be a gameſter. Talk of God who liſt, they will talke of gaming. Naie, euen in praier time, when they haue giuen eare a little, they muſt talk of yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nights good fellowſhip, and what they ſhall doe in the afternoone. Good Lord what ſeruing of God call you this? Would not they thinke it an abſurd thing, to talke of anie matter of diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, when they are ſet at cardes? And is it not much more abſurd to talke of card matters in praier time? I tremble at the remembraunce of that irreuocable ſentence that ſhall be pronounſed ouer them, when they ſhall be called to iudgement. The Lord for his mercies ſake take the miſt from their eies, and then I knowe they will ſée their ſinnes,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:2469:64"/> and repent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Demas.</speaker>
                  <p>Amongſt all other euils, me think this game ſhould bring beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie. For the game it ſelf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> aſketh great charges, and they are hindered by this meanes, both from dooing good to others, and from getting anie thing in their calling: ſo that except they plaie vpon the vauntage, it is an hundred to one that they ſhall bee baggered by it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſaie true, for when they win anie thing, yet becauſe it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth ſo lightlie, it muſt go as light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie &amp; (as <hi>Tullie</hi> ſaith) <hi>Quod adopti ſunt per ſcelus, per luxuriam offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt.</hi> The thing that deceiueth them is this. Whatſoeuer they winne, it commeth vnlooked for, &amp; that is trim. They neuer marke that when they winne, ſomewhat goeth out: and that when they léeſe, nothing is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen backe. They neuer marke what griping vſurers dice and cardes are. For if you receiue anie thing of them to daie, you muſt not looke to go by the yere, nor yet by the
<pb facs="tcp:2469:65"/> moneth: you muſt paie your princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal, and twiſe ſo much more perhaps to morrow. It is wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derful to ſée, how blind, and how fooliſh men bée. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue a minde to a ring<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or to anie pretie conceit, they will venture their monie for it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome loſſe, when they refuſe to bie it right out. Héereof commeth it, that ſchollers comming from the vniuerſitie, maie rifle away their bookes, when they cannot ſell them, &amp; what fondnes is this? Euerie man knoweth that it is great follie, to hope certeinly for an vncertein thing: but to lay a wager of it, that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which they vncerteinlie looke for, ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teinlie come to paſſe, is méere mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. It is thought a goodlie matter of poore men, if rich men will take them as their companions: ſo likewiſe is it with gameſters. For though manie of them be men of no great wealth, yet hope is rich: and ſo long as they plaie, they ſhall be accompanied with rich hope. Though they bée in loſſe, yet lucke they thinke maie tourne. Their propheſieng is
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:2469:65"/> like the ſouthſaieng of a countreie A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtronomer, that I haue heard of, which thought that after a daie or two of raine, we ſhall haue fairer weather: but ſometimes (this laſt harueſt for example) his ſouthſaieng deceiued him twentie daies together. So gameſters thinke, that after an houre or two of ill lucke, the Cardes will goe on their ſide an other while: but their propheſieng deceiueth them ſo long till at the laſt it can deceiue them no more. You ſhall ſometimes ſée manie luſtie gallants, that becauſe they will giue the companie to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that they are able to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine franke plaie, and that they are no pidlers, they looſe all the monie in their purſſe: then muſt they borrow vpon vſurie, by which meanes they runne ſo farre in the laſh, that their reuenewes muſt be ſolde, and they ſtript into their dublet and their hoſe. Plaie muſt they néeds, and that they plaie for is in hazard, ſo that they can not rightlie call any thing theirs. For their watching ſo pauleth them, and
<pb facs="tcp:2469:66"/> the loue of ſport and companie ſo oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupieth their head, that they haue no leaſure to conſider what the iſſue wil be. Afterward when they can get no monie to continue their ſport, they begin to awake out of their ſléepe, and to conſider more déepelie of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: and when by waieng the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter well, they haue found that a man can not liue without ſome mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, then conſult they with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues how to get ſomewhat. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they either know not, or béeing Gentlemen, are aſhamed to labour in ſome honeſt trade: They beginne to complaine of the griping and harde dealing of couetous men. What a world is this (ſaie they) that a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of loutes ſhould haue ſo much lieng by them? Why doe we conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue thus like ſlaues? Let vs rather ſhow our ſelues to be men of courage, let vs laie for ſome bootie, that wee maie braue it in Poules or in Cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide as we were wont. Their friends ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed oftentimes make friends, and kéepe them from the gallowes: but<note place="margin">Pro. 11. 21.</note>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:2469:66"/> yet (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith) though hand ioine in hand, the wicked ſhall not be vnpuniſhed. They bootie it ſo long, till at ſome gallowes or other, they become an open ſpectacle of the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God vnto the whole world, and a fearefull warning (if they be wiſe) to all thoſe that followe their ſteps. Examples they ſaie are verie fitte to teach withall, and yet we are ſo doltiſh in learning anie kinde of goodneſſe, that manifeſt and plaine examples can teach vs no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. I remember, whileſt I was in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> A ſimple man at his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution willed ſchollers in anie caſe to take héede of gaming, that brought him to that ſhamefull ende: and yet, becauſe in his exhortation he vſed an auke phraſe to expreſſe his mind with all, I am afraid (ſaid he) you will forgette my exhalations, as ſoone as you are out of the Caſtle gates: Becauſe (I ſaie) hée ſpake a word amiſſe, we ieſted at the phraſe, and ſo by this meanes, the goodneſſe that we ſhould haue learned by his
<pb facs="tcp:2469:67"/> fearefull ende, was put by: whereas if we had loked vpon the matter wel, his words, at that time, ought to haue bene of as great authoritie, as anie Doctors word in <hi>Cambridge.</hi> But this miſchiefe doth not raine in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> and <hi>Cambridge</hi> alone: for euerie towne, eſpeciallie if it be of anie big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is infected with this euill. Euen in this towne not long ſince, there was a man that had a good dowrie with his wife, and was verie well to liue of himſelfe: yet by this miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous gaming, he was quite vndone: and to redéeme himſelfe out of priſon, his wife &amp; his children were throwne out of dores. Surelie it would haue pitied a mans heart to haue ſéene it: hée himſelfe being left to the wide world, no man knoweth what wilbe become of him, wher by the waie are confuted y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> fond pitifull words, which are wont to be vſed in defence of ſuch riotous perſons. Alas (ſaie they) it is great pitie: he was no mans foe but his owne: for héere we maie ſee, that they are foes to a great manie. The
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:2469:67"/> common wealth might well looke to haue ſome reliefe towards the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of their poore: but now muſt they and their children be kept with the goods of the poore: ſo that the poore in the pariſh, which ſhould otherwiſe haue bene well prouided for, are pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and miſerablie vexed, and all through gaming. How true doe wée finde that, which the Scripture ſaith, He that loueth paſtime ſhall be a poore<note place="margin">Pro. 21. 17.</note> man. Men maie call it a ſport, but it was the waightieſt matter, that euer he dealt withall in his life. If men rioted in apparrell, or in meates and drinkes, becauſe a mans vndoing this waie is not ſo ſoddaine: men commonlie are their friends, by coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell to remedie the matter, before all bée gone. But the vndooing of a man ſelfe by plaie is ſo ſodaine, that he is vnder the Ice, before a man can be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Demas.</speaker>
                  <p>Indéede as you ſaie, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie come to beggerie by this meanes: but yet all doe not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>Though men of large
<pb facs="tcp:2469:68"/> reuenewes are not beggered, yet they begger a great manie by this means. Their tenaunts are miſerablie pinch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed through their Land-lord his follie: whereas, if this vile moneie game were left, they would no doubt deale better with them, and be more bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Lords to poore men: we ſhould not then haue ſuch forfeiting of lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and ſuch oppreſſing of men as we haue. What an abſurd thing is it, that men ſhould kéepe ſuch a coile for moneie, and when they haue it caſt awaie? I knowe there bée a great manie pennie fathers, which though they looſe nothing at gaming, yet gripe poore men: but yet I knowe there be a great manie, that if they loſt and ſpent not ſo much at plaie, would bée more frank-hearted to poore men, then they are. Doth the Lord finde fault with the vnprofitable ſeruaunt, that laid not out his talent to his maſters aduauntage, but hid it in the ground? And will he not iudge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſeruant that waſteth it vpon trifles? The holie Ghoſt commandeth vs to honour the<note place="margin">Pro. 3. 9.</note>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:2469:68"/> Lord with our riches. And the Iewes, to giue vs to vnderſtand, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were redie to beſtow their goods at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords appointment were willed to paie the firſt fruits to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord of all that euer they had: but do we honour him with our goods (thinke you) when we trifle them away at cards &amp; tables. But ſin hath no ſtaie with it. For it is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for vs, thus vnthankfullie to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good gifts of God, except we ſin directly againſt himſelfe. What chola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick paſſions (I pray you) are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> looſers toſſed withall, gentlemen or other: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cannot chafe, is accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a ſenceles block. And becauſe they dare not giue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole diſpoſition of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dice vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, leaſt in finding falt therwith they ſhuld open their mouth againſt him: they ſet vp an Idoll to their imaginations. I wil ſet out his hand (ſaie they) in deſpite of the dice. Did euer man hold out ſo long, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſo manie points to enter? What fortune is this? What lucke is this? I care not ſo much for the monie, but to ſée what ſpitefull lucke I haue.
<pb facs="tcp:2469:69"/> Then muſt the Cards be rent in pée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or the Dice throwne into the fire: and yet they will laugh at a little child which beateth the ground for giuing him a fall. I ſpeake fauourablie of them, for they are ſo farre from thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that they ſhall giue account for euerie angrie and idle word, that they thinke of no account for foming out ſuch blaſphemies againſt the bleſſed name of God: and that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo not in vaine alone, as others doe, which are no gameſters to confirme euerie trifle, (for they ſweare not to ende anie controuerſie,) but becauſe God ordereth the Dice no better for them, therefore do they ſpue out blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies againſt him. For why els ſhould they ſweare by him? Naie, they themſelues re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der this reſon that I haue brought, why they ſweare. It would make one ſweare (ſaie they) to haue ſuch lucke. Of a truth, God is long ſuffering, to ſée if they will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. For els he would neuer ſtaie to take them awaie by ordinarie ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, as he vſeth to deale with others:
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:2469:69"/> but he would cauſe the earth to ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them vp into eternall confuſion, euen whileſt the oathes are in their mouthes, ſuch open contempners of him. And although y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> partie that plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with them, beginneth to tremble for feare: yet he muſt not reprooue him. For then he looketh vppon him with firie eies, and is readie to thruſt his dagger into him: he accounteth then that he hath great iniurie, for loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers muſt haue their ſaieng. So that a man muſt, either by reproouing bée in daunger of outrage: or els, by his ſilence he muſt be acceſſarie to open treaſon againſt the almightie. So that whether you looke to the winner, or to the looſer, they are both guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie (euen by the iudgement of ſinfull fleſh) of moſt grieuous ſinne againſt the Lord God. What is the cauſe of drunkenneſſe, but this beaſtlie game? For if the companie were not conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued with fluſh, and ace of ſpades, king a diamonds, and ſuch like ſtuffe: if I ſaie men were not kept ſtill at the Alehouſe with this fond talke, by
<pb facs="tcp:2469:70"/> that time they had ben together a litle while, they could not tell what to ſaie one to another: they would then goe from their cups, before that ſtaring &amp;<note place="margin">Pro. 23. 29.</note> redneſſe of the eies, that the ſcripture ſpeaketh of, came vppon them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Demas.</speaker>
                  <p>When a man doth tell game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, that theſe fruits that you haue ſpoken of, come by plaie: their aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere is, that theſe be the faultes of men that abuſe their ſport, and not of the game it ſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>Thoſe that aunſwere ſo, you maie aſke them, how they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues knowe anie thing: for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. How doe they knowe that a tale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearer cauſeth contention. They will aunſwere, by the effect of the matter: it alwaies falleth out ſo. So doe I know, and ſo maie they know, that a thouſand more miſchiefes then I haue ſpoken of, doe come of dice-plaie. If they ſaie, that there be not theſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chifes in the game, if gameſters were as they ſhould be: ſo can I ſaie, that a tale-bearer cannot cauſe contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if the partie to whom the tale is
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:2469:70"/> told, were as he ſhould be: and yet we ſaie, a talebearer cauſeth contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: &amp; we maie as trulie ſaie, that dice and cards cauſe ſuch miſchiefes as are ſpoken of. When a ſtatute was made by Act of Parliament, againſt vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full games, did not the Knights and Burgeſſes, being aduertiſed by the communaltie, whoſe patrones they are? Did not they perceiue what hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible miſchiefes broke out into the common wealth.</p>
                  <p>For want of reſtraint that waies? Did not the Lords and Nobles of the vpper houſe, ſée that their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint was iuſt, and that they laide the fault where it was, when they confirmed that, which they deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? And héere haue all good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences iuſt cauſe to complaine. For, what a ſhameful thing is it, that ſuch an honourable aſſemblie ſhould be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, from euerie part of the lande, to make ſo good and ſo notable a law: and yet, that thorough the looſe negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of thoſe that haue that truſt committed vnto them, to ſée theſe
<pb facs="tcp:2469:71"/> lawes executed, all ſhould be to no purpoſe? Naie, I ſpeake fauourablie of them: for they doe not onelie not puniſh theſe vnlawfull games, but with their authoritie they licenſe a companie of néedeleſſe Alehouſes, which are places of refuge for naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie packes to lurke in. And though for verie ſhame, they be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled to take awaie their licenſe from ſome dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Alehouſe, that for maintaining of wickedneſſe is more notable then the reſt: yet, if ſome wicked rich ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpeak a good word for them, they ſhall haue leaue to be maſters of as much euill rule as euer they wer. And what man cannot make ſome friend or other to ſpeake for him? If they can ſaie that they are poore men, all is well. But why ſhould not they worke for their liuing as well as other poore men? Why haue they more reſpect to the pouertie of one, then to the beggering of al the poore men in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> towne? They ſay men maie chuſe whether they wil ſpende their moneie at the Alehouſe or no: but poore women, &amp; their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:2469:71"/> can not chuſe whether their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands ſhal ſpend that at the alehouſe, that ſhould be for their maintenance, or no. Beſide this, if me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> could gouerne themſelues, to what purpoſe ſhould they be appointed gouernours of a towne? For they are ſet in authoritie aboue their bretheren, to the end they might ouerrule and gouerne ſuch, as cannot gouerne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. Thoſe that beare office, are ſworne to put downe dice &amp; card-plaie: &amp; yet, if they kéepe an alehouſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, they wil allure poore men to theſe vnlawfull games, and rather then they ſhould not play, they will play with them themſelues. This hath bene told to him that may remedie the matter, &amp; yet there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing done. A notable iudgement of God hath bene ſhewed vpon periured perſons at <hi>Thaxted,</hi> not farre hence: and yet are we not afraid to forſweare our ſelues. Séeing therefore theſe things are thus, I beſéech the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher in the name of the liuing God, that he wold not ſooth vp the officers: as if all things were well, when in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déede
<pb facs="tcp:2469:72"/> there is onlie a vaine flouriſh of diſcipline vſed, which is as much as nothing. For, who knoweth not that theſe games are vſed? &amp; yet who hath ben reprooued for it? Ther be (indéed) gouernours appointed, but ther is not that diligent inquiring after theſe things, as ſhuld be: &amp; yet when things are complained of, other men are not diſcouraged from ſin by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the offender. The Magiſtrate thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth that he doth diſcharge his dutie highlie, if he puniſheth when a falt is brought before him: otherwiſe, though they heare men ſwearing at cards, as they walke in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtréetes, it maketh no matter. Good Lord, wher is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> merciful ſeueritie that was: in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> good man <hi>Iob,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>b. 29. 8. &amp; 6.</note> which made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnrulie young me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hide themſelues for feare, when they ſaw him? He did not waite til a complaint was brought to him but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he knew not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe, he ſought it out dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlie. This thing, as all other things wer, was written for our lerning: we muſt therfore do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like. We ſhuld put down all vitling houſes, but ſuch as muſt
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:2469:72"/> néedes be had to intertaine ſtraung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, thoſe vitling houſes that remain, we muſt ſearch them diligentlie, &amp; if there be anie cards or tables found, we muſt bring them to the market place, &amp; there burne them before all the people. And if the Law will giue vs leaue, we ſhuld take all the cards &amp; tables out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> haberdaſhers ſhops, &amp; burne them. I know not what the Lawe ſaith in this point, but trulie I can ſée no reaſon, how it can be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to buie or ſel cards or tables, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is forbidden. Idle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons muſt be hunted after, at ſuch pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as are ſuſpected, their haunt muſt be broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: then ſhal y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth bring forth her increaſe, and God (euen our owne God) ſhall giue vs his bleſſing. If the Preacher be afraid to preach theſe things (as we are all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſort of vs co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards &amp; daſtards in Gods matters) if we be afraid, we know of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to aſke ſtrength, euen of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mightie &amp; valiant God, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is fierce in battell, the Lord of hoſts is his name. What art thou (faith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet <hi>Eſay)</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou ſhuldeſt<note place="margin">Eſaie. 51</note>
                     <pb facs="tcp:2469:73"/> feare a mortal man, and the ſonne of man, which ſhall be made as graſſe, and forgetteſt the Lord thy maker, that hath ſpred out the heauens? Let vs not therefore feare the reproch of men, for their breath is in their no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrells, &amp; the moath ſhal eate them vp like a garment, &amp; the worme ſhal eate them like wooll. If we will not ſpeak, the Lord is a iealous God. Truſſe vp thy loines (ſaith the Lord vnto <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie)</hi> ariſe, and ſpeake vnto the people all that I command thée, be not afraid of their faces, leaſt I deſtroie thée be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them. If thou haſt this boldnes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thée, though men fight againſt thée, they ſhall not preuaile: the Lord (euen the Lord ſhal deliuer thée. Thou muſt not ceaſe from ſpeaking, when ſome little abuſe is amended. Wicked king <hi>Pharao</hi> yéelded ſomwhat to <hi>Moſes</hi> pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticion, but <hi>Moſes</hi> would not content himſelfe with a litle. The Lord muſt haue an abſolute obedience. We muſt indéed yéelde obedience to all magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, good and badde: ſo that it be in the Lord: but yet we muſt not
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:2469:73"/> commend them before they walke roundlie in their office, as they ſhuld. No, no, if the officers did their due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, we ſhuld not haue ſuch diſorders as we haue. If a ſubtile fellowe, to make thoſe that ſhould looke to it ſecure, giue it out, that plaie is well ceaſed: then all is ſafe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Demas.</speaker>
                  <p>But you knowe the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates cannot puniſh men for plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng in Chriſtmas time: as they call it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>But they maie, and ought to puniſh them to: for euen then, when they haue moſt libertie, they muſt not plaie at Alehouſes: but in their maiſters houſe, or when their mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter looke on them, when an inch is giuen they muſt not take an ell: but I haue before ſhewed the abuſe of this time, and therefore I will not ſpeake of it anie more.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Demas.</speaker>
                  <p>You haue done ſo indéed: but yet you haue not aunſwered one reſon that hath bene vſed in defence of abuſing the time, in this order. The reaſon is taken out of the third
<pb facs="tcp:2469:74"/> Chapter of the Preacher, where the wiſe man ſaith, that to all things ther is an appointed time: and that there is a time to caſt awaie ſtones, or to trifle (as they expound it.)</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet caſting of ſtones, were a great deale better exerciſe, then to ſit moping and dreaming at a paire of cards. But the truth is, they ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie abuſe the place. For it hath bene proued before, that whether wée eate or drinke, or whatſoeuer we doe, we muſt doe it to the glorie of God. When we exerciſe or recreate our ſelues, our recreation muſt tend to edifieng, and to the building vp of our faith: for example. When we plaie at tennis, we refreſh our wearied ſpirits and memories, by the which meanes we are better able to ſtudie, and to get knowledge, whereby our faith is ſtrengthened. For aunſwere to their place, this I ſaie, that the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Ghoſt doth not ſet downe what maie be done without breach of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: but he telleth vs what is commonlie done among men, as it is
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:2469:74"/> plaine in the text, &amp; as it is eaſie to perceiue by the argument of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole booke. Among other thinges that are there rehearſed, it is ſaid, that ther is a time to hate, and a time to loue: but we knowe, there is no time, wherein we ought for to hate. If anie alledge, that we ought to hate ſin, they ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> purpoſe. For our hatred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſin, muſt not be reſtrained to anie one time: but we muſt bid it bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle all our life. But ther it is euident that the text ſpeaketh of the diuerſitie of time, ſo that they are ſtill to ſéeke for the defence of their vanities.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Demas.</speaker>
                  <p>If the lewde example of the vniuerſitie were not, truly I thinke, and partlie by report I vnderſtand ſo much, that manie Gentlemen would leaue this game: and alſo cauſe all their houſehold to leaue it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>I will not defend y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vniuerſitie in this ſin of theirs, notwithſtanding ſo far foorth as the truth will giue me leaue, I will ſpeake ſomwhat in their defence. Leaſt therefore anie ſhould think worſe of <hi>Cambridge</hi> men, then
<pb facs="tcp:2469:75"/> they deſerue, this I can ſaie: that all the maiſters of Colledges are aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of this game. For (as farre as I could euer learne) they neuer plaie publikelie: if they plaie at all, it is in hugger mugger. This alſo I can ſaie, that thoſe that vſed this game, were verie infamous, and generallie thought euill of, throughout the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie: and therefore thoſe that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued this ſport, were driuen to ſéeke corners. For they know that it was vnworthie the excellencie of a man, eſpeciallie of ſuch as profeſſe the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of wiſdome and learning, to bée ſéene plaieng at ſo doltiſh a game. I haue thought ere now, when I haue ſéene ſchollers holding thrée ſhort thicke péeces of paper in their hand, with ſuch great and goutie ſpots vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them, I haue thought (I ſaie) that it hath ben the moſt ill fauoured ſight that euer I ſawe: a booke of a ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler print would become their hands a great deale better, what an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéemelie thing is it, that men of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſhould be heard talking of a
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:2469:75"/> paire of eights, or a paire of tennes, of two aſes, and .xxj. Euerie plaine man in the countrie can ſkill of this arethmatick. But they muſt plaie for the Butlers aduantage, &amp; they muſt ſurfet and be ſicke for the Phiſitions aduantage. Students commonlie ſit too much, and therefore they haue no néede of this ſitting paſtime. But cannot the Butler be mainteined, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the poore ſchollers (for loue of this ſport) ſell their bookes, and their ſhéetes from vnder them? They know, or ought to knowe, that we muſt not doe euill that good maie come thereof. Is it not a more eaſie matter to find their Butler, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they put him to no charges, then when they cauſe him to bie cards, counters, and candelles? Will men of wealth (thinke you) giue anie exhibition, when you trifle awaie your monie at poſt and paire? Will men haue anie mind to ſend their children to you, when you let them run at rouers, in the moſt daungerous time of their age, ſo long together? If young men
<pb facs="tcp:2469:76"/> could gouerne themſelues, wherefore ſerue Maiſters? Wherfore ſerue Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors? is it to be thought y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g youths haue more hold of themſelues, &amp; maie better be without gouernment, in ſo ſlippery a thing as gaming is, then in other matters. Is not gaming y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> giueth a fall to men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are of a ſtaied age? Séeing therfore theſe things are thus, I humblie beſéech all maiſters of Colledges, &amp; all thoſe that can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme this abuſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they wuld not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to be carried away with a popiſh &amp; a doting cuſtome: I beſéech them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they wuld conſider, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> therfore do me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take ſuch paines at their booke, not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhould take whatſoeuer a blinde cuſtome doth offer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (for it is ſoone ſéene without anie learning, what is done:) but a diligent inquirie after that which ought to be done wil aſke a lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger ſtudie. I beſéech the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bowels of Ieſus Chriſt, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they loue their own ſoules health, &amp; the health of thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are ſo déerelie bought, euen with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> precious bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhedding of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſon of God, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they wuld
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:2469:76"/> reforme this diſorder, &amp; ſend this rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to <hi>Rome,</hi> from whence it came. I know they are wiſe men, &amp; it may be, ſome men thinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my giuing of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> counſell will be to no purpoſe: but yet <hi>Apollos</hi> was a verie eloquent &amp; a wiſe man, &amp; we read of him, that he was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to be reformed by a poore crafts man. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wiſeſt man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer was, ſaith, that if you reproue a wiſe man, he will loue you, &amp; increaſe in wiſdome. I haue ben bold therfore to giue admonition to theſe wiſe men, &amp; I am in good hope, that they will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, not my counſell, but the counſell of the onelie wiſe God. But if they will be a froward people, &amp; a ſtifneck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed generation, they will conſtraine y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſimple men of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> countrie to take vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaieng of Chriſt againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I thank thée (O father) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou haſt hid theſe things from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wiſe &amp; prudent, &amp; haſt reuealed them vnto babes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by this means others maie be ſtaied fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>b<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at them. But I cannot thus ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie my ſelfe, with putting by the offence y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they giue. I deſire therefore
<pb facs="tcp:2469:77"/> all thoſe that aime at examples ſo much, that they would conſider, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Phyſition doth not alwaies ſquare his life by the rules of phyſicke: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth the Lawyer alwaies ſquare his dooing by the lawe: nor the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine by diuinitie. If we be ſicke, we aſke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Phiſition what counſell he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, we doe not require after his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et. Neither if we wuld know a truth in anie matter of diuinitie, are we to looke to the life of a diuine: for then we maie ſoone be deceiued. If wée looke vpon the examples of a grat ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie now reſidents, we ſhall take rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Curates to be as good men as they are, we ſhall be made to beléeue by their examples, that it made no matter whether there were anie preaching, or no. But when they come among their Curates, they will tell them that it is a farre more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent matter to preach then to read an Homelie: And when they make a ſermon, they will tell the people (as the truth is in déede) that preaching is the mightie power of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:2469:77"/> God, to drawe vs from our accurſed eſtate, that by nature we are in, that there is no other ordinarie meanes, whereby the Lord worketh ſaluation in our hearts. For no man can heare without a Preacher. They will tell you, that the loue of paſtors towards Chriſt and his flocke, muſt be iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by féeding: becauſe Chriſt ſaith vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> féede, féede, feede. So dare I ſaie for <hi>Cambridge</hi> men, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer their examples are, that if a Gentleman come to them, that is ſomewhat doubtfull in this point, and aſke them whether the rioting that they vſe in Chriſtmas time, is allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed off by the word of God, or no: I dare ſaie for them, that they will giue ſentence againſt their own example. I preſume the rather y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are againſt theſe games, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I cannot thinke that they dare open their mouths againſt ſuch an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of learned men, as haue in all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges condemned them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Demas.</speaker>
                  <p>Trulie ſir, I thinke it were verie good, that the iudgement of
<pb facs="tcp:2469:78"/> learned men, that are knowne to bée men of credit, and are generallie wel thought of, were gathered together, &amp; put in print, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth might haue ſome continuance by them. For though (indéede) the bare authorities of men be little worth in themſelues: yet becauſe, when men that are fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for their wiſedome and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſhall be known to write againſt anie thing: men will then common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie make inquirie after the reaſons that cauſe them to write, as they doe: I ſaie in this reſpect, it were good to alleadge the authoritie of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>The authorities and the reaſons of the moſt excellent au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors that we haue, are alreadie ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together by two learned di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> and <hi>Danzus,</hi> againſt this vile game, that idle heads make ſuch account of, and are in print in the handes of a great manie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Demas.</speaker>
                  <p>I but ſir, euerie bodie doth not vnderſtande the language that
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:2469:78"/> they write in.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue gathered out and ſet down in Engliſh moſt of the authors that they alleadge: and I haue partlie amplified them with other mens iudgements that came to my minde. And if you will ſtaie a little, you ſhall heare what they ſaie.</p>
                  <p>Firſt before I begin, we muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that our lawes haue appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted puniſhment for thoſe that vſe this game: it hath alreadie paſſed the condemnation of our countrie. The ciuill lawe that is more generall then ours, doth likewiſe condemne it in ſundrie places. If <hi>F.</hi> ſaith <hi>Pretor de alcat.</hi> If anie ſhall call foorth his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe to plaie, let him be puniſhed, &amp; caſt in priſon. The Emperour <hi>Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> would not ſuffer anie of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects to vſe this game, either in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like or priuate houſes: neither would he ſuffer anie to loke vpon theſe that did plaie. If anie thing were loſt that waies, there was lawe to recouer it againe. <hi>Liber. 3. Codicis Iuſtine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anei. Tit. 43.</hi> The <hi>Romanes</hi> prouided
<pb facs="tcp:2469:79"/> 
                     <hi>Lege Roſcia,</hi> that thoſe which loſt their monie this waies ſhould be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. In <hi>Tullie</hi> his time, when the <hi>Romanes</hi> flouriſhed in all kinde of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance, (at which time men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monlie vſe moſt rioting:) yet euen then was it accounted a ſhamefull matter to be a dice plaier. For <hi>Tullie</hi> going about, &amp; bending all the force of his wit to bring <hi>Cataline,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Anthonie</hi> into the hatred of the ſenate, &amp; the reſt of the people, he tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were dicers: which thing he would neuer haue done, if to plaie at dice had not bene an odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thing with them. The Poets are wont to match whooredome and dice plaie together.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hunc damnoſa Venus, tunc pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps alia prodit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iuuenal</hi> ſaith, that it doth corrupt<note place="margin">Satyra. 1.</note> whole families. Maiſter <hi>Aſcham,</hi> that was Schoolemaſter to the Quéenes maieſtie, bringeth in <hi>Chauſer</hi> our Engliſh Poet inueieng againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed bones: &amp; he himſelfe in his booke of ſhooting, would haue it made a matter
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:2469:79"/> of fellonie. In the Canons of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, this game is plainlie forbidden: <hi>Cano. 41</hi> Euen the Canon lawe that was gathered of the Papiſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, doth verie ſeuerelie condemne it <hi>Decretalium. lib. 3. Tit. 1. c.</hi> Now if we will come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godlie fathers of the Church, we ſhall ſée, that both old &amp; new haue condemned it. The godly man <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diuel was the firſt deuiſer of this game. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,</hi> in his firſt booke of offices. 23. Chapter. And <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> in his. 6. Homelie vpon <hi>Mathew,</hi> inuaie vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentlie againſt it. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle. 54. would haue whatſoeuer is gotten this waies taken from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and beſtowed vpon the poore, by this meanes (ſaith he) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gréedie game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſhall be depriued of that he look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth &amp; gapeth for: and the fooliſh fellow that loſt his monie ſhall be puniſhed. <hi>Nicholas Lyra,</hi> that was accounted the beſt learned in his time, wrote a booke called <hi>Preceptorium,</hi> wherein he proueth by nine reaſons. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our talke is of authohities, his
<pb facs="tcp:2469:80"/> reaſons were gathered out of ſundrie authors, wherby he proued y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dice play was not to be ſuffered in a Chriſtian co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth. The godly man <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> writing to the godlie ſouldiers y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelleth them to be at defiance with dice play. <hi>Peter Martyr.</hi> vpon the .xiiij. Chapter of the Iudges, ſaith, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our monie is giuen vs of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord to nouriſh our families, and to prouide for ſuch as haue néed: beſide this, we Chriſtians are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the image of God, which doth not anie thing at a venture, &amp; at hap hazard. For he waieth the waters by meaſure, as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith: &amp; ſaith vnto the proud waues of the ſea, thus far ſhalt thou come. We therefore muſt do the like, and not ſet our moneie at ſix and ſeuen. <hi>Danzus,</hi> in his booke <hi>de Ludo,</hi> ſaith, that deceit is ſo incident to dice, that the Apoſtle in the fourth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fourtenth verſe, vſeth that word that doth properlie ſignifie dice<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 5. 22</note> for deceit &amp; guile. He telleth vs, out of the Apoſtle, that we muſt abſteine euen from the appearance of euill. If
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:2469:80"/> (ſaith he) <hi>Paule</hi> would abſteine from fleſh all his life long, rather then his weake brother ſhould be offended: it is a ſhame for vs, if we ſhould not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteine fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo trifling a thing, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may ſo well be ſpared, ſéeing there are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt recreations enough, when ſuch horrible miſchiefes continuallie come thereby. By theſe, &amp; manie other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> haue ben partlie ſpoken of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, he is bold to ſaie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the moneie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is gotten by plaie, is vniuſtlie kept: &amp; with no better conſcience, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a théefe kepeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which he hath ſtoln. M. <hi>Iewel</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> latter end of his apologie, reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth &amp; alloweth very wel of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doing of one <hi>Gobilo, a Lacedemonian,</hi> which whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was ſent ambaſſador to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Corinth,</hi> to treat of a league, &amp; had found y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dice was commonlie vſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, he returned home again w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his meſſage vndone: and being aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſent him, why he did ſo, he made anſwere, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhuld be a gret reproch to his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monwelth, to make a legue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dicers. <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of gret reading, miſliketh y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhould ſuffer
<pb facs="tcp:2469:81"/> our children to vſe this kind of game, when we buie our ſelues a new paire of cards, we wuld not haue vs let our children plaie with our olde. For it is better a great deale, that our cardes ſhould be loſt, then that we ſhould léeſe our cards &amp; our children too. Of all other men he could not abide that Prieſts, as he called them, ſhould vſe this game. If he had ſéene a Bible, &amp; a paire of tables lieng together in a Biſhops hall, he would haue thought it a foule fault. For theſe two cleaue together like claie &amp; yron, as <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpeaketh, they are not matches. God will be no baude to our naughtines, the ſcripture muſt not be pretended where dice play is ment. Euen <hi>Caſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o</hi> the courtier, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> laboureth altogether in framing of an outward ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, though not altogether in wordes, yet in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie déede he doth vtterlie condemne dice and cards. His words be theſe, I thinke it no vice in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> courtier to play at dice &amp; cards, except (marke his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) except a man applie it to much, &amp; by reaſon of that, ſetteth aſide other
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:2469:81"/> things more neceſſarie: or els for none other intent, then to get moneie, &amp; to beguile his fellow, &amp; in his loſſe fume &amp; take on, ſo that it might be thought a token of couetouſneſſe. What man is he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vſeth this play, that plaieth not too much? For the looſer will not giue ouer, and he that winneth, muſt not leaue his fellowe in the lurch. Who by plaieng thereat, ſetteth not aſide better things? Who plaieth not to get moneie? Who deceiueth not? Who chafeth not? For this cauſe, <hi>Ouid</hi> in his Courtier (vnleſſe I be deceiued) giueth a louer warning to take héede of plaieng before his Ladie or Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: becauſe it doeth laie open our beaſtlie affections, which might other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be kept ſecret. And ſo, by this means, a man ſhall not be ſo amiable to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> companie, as otherwiſe he ſhuld. This game maie verie well be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to water that is powred into a boule, which cauſeth a wooden ſpoone or anie ſuch light thing to ſwim aloft, that would otherwiſe haue bene be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath. <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> the Phiſition, of
<pb facs="tcp:2469:82"/> whom I ſpake before, writeth a whole treatiſe againſt this game: and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by manie philoſophicall reſons the beaſtlineſſe of it. It were verie long, and indéede infinite, to rehearſe thoſe that haue writ againſt it. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fauour this game giue me but one inſtance, let them ſhowe me, if they can, that anie learned man, Diuine, or other, which is otherwiſe knowne to be a man of iudgement, that if he ſpeake anie thing of it, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth it not. But becauſe they can not bring forth anie ſuch, let them not think themſelues wiſer then all other men: let them be content to followe the counſell of thoſe that bée wiſer then themſelues. For my part, I am wearie with laieng abroad this dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill of ſinne, and therfore I wil grow to a concluſion with it. The ſumme of that which I haue ſaid is this. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by vſuall words, and continuall practiſe of gameſters themſelues, this game is an Art, &amp; nothing els but a profeſſion to how deceiue cunninglie: Séeing, whether you looke to the effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:2469:82"/> materiall, formal, or final cauſe, or to the horrible fruits and effects that procéed from anie of them, it is naught: ſéeing it is no recreation. Séeing, laſt of all, it hath bene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in all ages, not onelie by the iudgement of manie learned Diuines olde and new, and of manie other that are otherwiſe learned, but alſo by the common conſent of whole countreies, common wealths, and kingdomes, I conclude: that dice and cards, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and wrangling barrators, are to be baniſhed the countrie.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>The remedie againſt ſuch euills, as haue bene hetherto ſpoken of. Chap. 6.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DEmas.</speaker>
                  <p>Trulie ſir, I doe not thinke that you haue ſpoken anie thing, to gall anie man, but onelie of méere loue: and therefore in my iudgement, you ſhould doe well, if you would ſet downe a remedie againſt ſuch faults as you haue diſcouered.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb facs="tcp:2469:83"/>Paule.</speaker>
                  <p>The Lord that ſhall iudge both me and all other at the laſt daie, can that loue towards my countreie, my natiue towne, and eſpeciallie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards my kindſ folke and bretheren, hath cauſed me to ſpeake as I haue done. And therefore I beſéech them, in the bowels of Ieſus Chriſt, that they would looke to theſe faults, that I haue laid before them, and amend them. I haue ſhewed them inéed, that their fault is more grieuous then per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps they take it to be. For how could I els admoniſh them at all? In the ninetéene of <hi>Leuiticus</hi> we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, that we ſhould not hate our brother: but rebuke him plainlie. If I had ſpoken coldlie, and a farre of, that had bene a waie to rock them a ſléepe in their ſinnes, they would haue thought then, that there is no daunger in continuing ſtill the courſe which they haue begun. For, as one trulie ſaith, hée that demaundeth a thing fearefullie, teacheth a man to denie him his demaund, and it is as true a principle in Diuinitie, as it is
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:2469:83"/> in Surgerie, that ſoft hands make a foule ſore. Deſiring them therefore to take this my proteſtation, as it is ment, I will goe on forward to that remedie you ſpeake of. In intreating of the which thing, I will betake my ſelfe to that ſame order, which I haue alreadie ſet downe. It hath bene ſaid, that we maie offend in vſing the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures of God, either too little, or too much. Concerning the firſt kind, thoſe that offend that waies, I would deſire them to conſider the inconueuience that commeth by their too much ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. For, when men abſolutelie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne hunting, hawking, or taking delight in anie pleaſure, men that vſe theſe delights too much, thinke that it is vnpoſſible, but that a man ſhould take pleaſure in the creatures of God, and indéede, they thinke aright: ſo, through too much ſtraitneſſe, they giue themſelues ouer to their accuſtomed delights, whereas, if the libertie that God hath graunted, were ſet downe, and men inſtructed in the right vſe thereof, it is to be hoped, that men
<pb facs="tcp:2469:84"/> would come to a godlie moderation in theſe things. I will therefoe alleadge ſuch texts of ſcripture, as maie reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die this too much ſeueritie. We are taught in the ſcripture, that if there were anie, who had not eaten y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruits of their labours, they ſhould retourne home euen in the vrgent neceſſitie of warres. A notable teſtimonie to ſhew how wel it liketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men ſhuld take comfort of their owne. The ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt delight that a man maie take in anie thing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the Lord beſtoweth vpon vs, is verie plainlie ſet downe in the parable of <hi>Nathan</hi> to <hi>Dauid.</hi> There was (ſaith he) a poore man, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had only one litle ſhéepe, which he had bought, &amp; noriſhed vp: &amp; it grew vp with him, &amp; with his children alſo, &amp; did eate of his owne murſels, and dranke of his owne cup, &amp; ſlept in his boſome, and was vnto him as his daughter. This delight doth ſo wel pleaſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, that in the Prouerbs it is ſet downe as a<note place="margin">Chap. 5. 18.</note> ſufferaine remedie againſt ſinne. For there y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holie Ghoſt diſſwading of vs from whoredome, willeth vs in anie
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:2469:84"/> caſe to take delight in our wiues. His words be theſe, Reioice with the wife of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> youth, let her be as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> louing hinde &amp; pleaſant Roe: let her breaſts ſatiſfie thée at all times: &amp; delight in her loue continuallie. For why ſhouldeſt thou delight (my ſonne) in a ſtrange woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or imbrace the boſome of a ſtranger? If theſe texts doe not proue plainlie enough, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man maie vſe recreatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, let vs heare what <hi>Zacharie</hi> ſaith. The<note place="margin">Chap. 8. 5.</note> Prophet foretelling the returne of the <hi>Iewes</hi> from their captiuitie, ſetteth it downe in theſe words: The citie ſhal be ful of boies &amp; girles, plaieng in the ſtréets thereof: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord knoweth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we cannot alwaies haue our mind bent &amp; faſtned vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> waightie matters, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he hath giuen vs leaue to vnbend our wits, &amp; to leaue of our hold, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh our weriſom ſpirits: to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end we might come to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> again w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> greater de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which ſome allege, is nothing. They ſaie, we muſt giue account for euery idle word, &amp; much more for ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our time in this order: but when I delight my ſelfe ſome honeſt waie,
<pb facs="tcp:2469:85"/> to the ende I might be fitter and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter able afterward to do better things, where as otherwiſe my memorie would be dulled, and vnapt to good meditations, I doe not now ſpend my time in vaine, but to good purpoſe. To vſe ſuch things as maie moue me chéerefullie to giue thankes, is no vaine paſtime. They ſaie we muſt reioice in the Lord onlie. The ſtaie in déed of our ioie muſt be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, he muſt be the reſting place of our ioie: but yet it hath bene proued, that wée maie reioice in his creatures. When we vſe the creatures as ſteppes to clime vppe to himſelfe: God then and his creatures are <hi>ſub alterna,</hi> as the Logitians vſe to ſpeak, one is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the other. They maie both ſtand together, the one doth not take awaie the other. There is another ſort of men that delight too much in the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature. The name of an Epicure is not liked of this kinde of men: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if it can bée proued vnto them, that the life of an Epicure is all one with theirs, there is ſome hope, that
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:2469:85"/> they will forſake this wicked ſect. <hi>Marcus Ciecro,</hi> writing of this kinde<note place="margin">De finibus.</note> of men, ſaith that they liked verie wel of wiſedome: becauſe thereby they knewe how to procure to themſelues ſuch things as are pleaſaunt, and to auoid all kind of griefe. They thought if a man did hazard himſelfe, to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer anie griefe, to the ende his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures might be increaſed, he was to be commended. Intemperate ſurfet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, becauſe it afterward brought griefe of bodie, and ſomewhat diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eted their merrie thoughts, they could not like of it. Doing of Iuſtice and liberalitie, becauſe it procured them the louing fauour of the people, they méetelie well allowed of. They were not ſuch drunken ſottes as we ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that would ſit gulling all daie long at the Alehouſe: No, they were iollie neat fellowes, and could behaue themſelues verie well, what compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſo euer they came into, as it maie be ſéene in that notable Epicure <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> in his Courtier, otherwiſe called his booke De arte amandi. They wold
<pb facs="tcp:2469:86"/> delight themſelues, either with ſuch pleaſures as are preſent, or with cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to minde ſuch pleaſant things as are paſt, or els w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a calme &amp; quiet loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king after ſuch things as wer to come. The end of one paſtime, was alwaies the beginning of another. Labouring in an honeſt trade, they did not like of: becauſe it was not pleaſant. Now let gameſters iudge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, &amp; ſée whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be of this ſect or no. A re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie againſt the continuall deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of our ſelues in the things of this world, is ſet downe in infinite places of the ſcripture. We are taught that we are pilgrimes &amp; ſtrangers in this world, and that we haue not héere a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie abiding citie: Our conuerſation muſt be in the heauens, from whence we looke for a Sauiour. The time is<note place="margin">Cor. 71.</note> ſhort, and therefore he that reioiceth, muſt be as if he reioiced not. All fleſh is graſſe, and the glorie thereof as the flower of the field. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>anitie of vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties (ſaith the Preacher) all is vanitie. The whole booke of <hi>Ecleſiaſtes</hi> is of this matter. Chriſt telleth vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wher
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:2469:86"/> our treaſure is, there will our hearts be alſo. We maie therfore deceiue our ſelues, and ſay, we looke to be ſaued as well as the beſt: but the ſcripture wil not beare vs out in anie ſuch ſpeach: for, if there wer anie treaſure laid vp for vs in heauen, our meditations, our talke, our doings, though they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of earthlie matters: yet they ſhuld tend to an heauenlie end. For where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as our treaſure is, there will our hearts be alſo. The delicate fellowes of this world, can not abide, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man ſhould be ſorrowfull for his ſinnes. What néed ſuch a buſineſſe (ſay they) do not men know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God is merciful? The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſhould be a foole by their reckning, for all his pſalmes are full of ſighing &amp; ſobbing for offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſo good a God. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> reioiced, &amp; did as it were triumph, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly ſorrow of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>Corinths.</hi> What great care hath it wrought? Yea, what cléering of your ſelfe? Yea what indignatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? yea, what feare? yea, how gret deſire? yea, what a zeale? yea, what puniſhment? &amp; indéed there was
<pb facs="tcp:2469:87"/> great cauſe why the Apoſtle ſhould thus reioice: for godlie ſorrow cauſeth repentaunce vnto ſaluation not to be repented of. What a pitifull thing is it, that a man ſhould imagine ſuch a kinde of repentaunce, as is no where to be found? For if we looke into that moſt mercifull promiſe of God, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his excéeding goodnes is abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſet out, Come vnto me all ye that labour and I will eaſe you: yet wée ſhall ſée, that it onelie belongeth vnto them, that are grieued with the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of their ſinnes. As long as wée make no more account of the bloudie ſweates and horrible torments that Chriſt ſuffered for vs miſerable men, then to ſaie, we are all ſinners: he will haue nothing to do with vs. For what is this, but blaſphemouſlie to accuſe the Lord God of méere tyrannie, for tormenting his onelie ſonne with ſuch agonies, reproch, &amp; villanie, and all (as we ſéeme to thinke) for a thing of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing? We muſt acknowledge our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption to be a benefit indéed, before he will doe vs anie good. He came not
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:2469:87"/> to call thoſe that make ſo light ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of ſinne. He came not to call the righteous, but ſiuners to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce. If they had once felt the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable ioie and comfort that this godlie ſorrow bringeth to a wounded conſcience, we ſhould ſoone agrée in this point. For to whom ſhall I looke (ſaith the Lord by his Prophet) but to him that trembleth at my words? A contrite and a broken heart (ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid)</hi> O Lord ſhalt not thou deſpiſe. The teares that come from the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, maie verie well be likened to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pril ſhowers, for they moiſten the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience as it were, with a ſwéet deaw, and make it (as the prophet ſpeaketh) like a new watred garden The ſwéet reconcilement then that Ieſus Chriſt hath wrought betweene God and vs, doth make vs féele more ſound ioie then the Epicures do in the midſt of Chriſtmas, euen in the twelfe night, when their iolitie is at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> higheſt. For being iuſtified by faith, we haue peace with God, &amp; if God doth iuſtifie, who ſhall condemne? Ieſus Chriſt that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="tcp:2469:88"/> vs, ſhall be our Iudge, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are bolde to looke &amp; long for, without feare, the iudgement daie, which the wicked are ſo afraid of. Thoſe that are gameſters cannot bée perſwaded, that we ſhould auoid the occaſions of euill: &amp; yet we all know, that he that will no harme doe, muſt doe nothing that belongs thereto. This is no preciſe rule. For that looſe fellowe <hi>Ouid</hi> in his booke <hi>De reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio amoris,</hi> doth ſet it downe. If wée miſlike of our former wantonnes, he telleth vs we muſt read no wanton books: we muſt auoid the company of thoſe with whom we haue abuſed our ſelues, euen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> places wher we haue a buſed our ſelues muſt be auoided: we muſt in no caſe be idle, but we muſt alway be buſied about ſome good mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The holie Ghoſt maketh ſuch ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> means, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lead vs vnto ſin, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he termeth the meanes by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of ſinne. We know the ſinnes of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom &amp; Gomor</hi> were monſtrous &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall: we know y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fulnes of bread, &amp; idleneſſe, were but the meanes that
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:2469:88"/> brought on thoſe vglie ſinnes: &amp; yet the Prophet <hi>Ezechiel</hi> ſaith, that the<note place="margin">Cap. 16. 49.</note> ſinnes of <hi>Sodom</hi> &amp; <hi>Gomor,</hi> were ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of bread, pride, and idleneſſe: the place is plaine inough, it néedeth no interpetation, onelie a godlie medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will ſerue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> turne. This kind of men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſpeake of, thinke that little ſinnes are not to be made account of: &amp; yet we will laugh at that fooliſh &amp; papiſticall diſtinction betwéene mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal &amp; veniall ſinnes. For whorebome, theft &amp; murder, is not that deadlie ſin that the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of? No ſinne is veniall, &amp; euerie ſin is deadlie. For<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 5. 16</note> the reward of ſinne is death, &amp; all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe is ſinne, as <hi>Iohn</hi> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs: &amp; accurſed is he that ſhall not continue in euerie thing that is written in the booke of the Law, to do it: &amp; we muſt loue the Lord with all our hearts, &amp; with al our thoughts. When men chafe at cards or at ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, we vſe to ſpeake fauourablie of this ſin. It is in their heat: but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward they are good fellowes againe. But the holie Ghoſt, when he intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb facs="tcp:2469:89"/> of this matter, he ſets it out after an other ſort. He that worketh wrath<note place="margin">Pro. 21. 24.</note> in his arrogancie, proud, hautie, and ſcornfull is his name. A théefe maie leſſen his ſinnes, by conſidering y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe of the partie, from whom he ſtealeth: he is a churle, and doth no good with his monie, and therefore it were a good turne to rob him. So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe may the murderer: if he be a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie man whom he killeth, he may ſay, he did him a good turne: if hée bée a wicked man that he killeth, then he did the common wealth a good turne: but where is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement of the great God all this while? It is true, that ſo long as we liue, the roote of ſinne ſhall dwell with vs, in our mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall bodie. We are not pure as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mileſt ſuppoſeth: but yet we muſt ſtriue to be pure, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. Luſt, after it hath conceiued, it bringeth forth ſin, as <hi>Iames</hi> teacheth. We ought therefore to be vexed and wearied w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it, &amp; to deſire after a pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent manner, to haue this tickle eſtate changed. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> crieth out,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:2469:89"/> not onelie in his owne perſon, but in the perſon of euerie regenerate man, Wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliuer me from this bodie of ſinne? If ſo ſinguler a man was not thro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughlie caſt downe, before hée had wraſteled with the iuſtice of God in this commaundement, we are to take héede leaſt in ſuſpecting y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to be in vs, which we want, we become careleſſe in ſéeking the mercie of Chriſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the which there is no helpe. We muſt iudge our ſelues, leaſt we bée iudged of the Lord: wée muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded in our ſelues, our deliuerie muſt be from the gates of death, wée muſt knowe, that our ſaluation doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſt in his frée grace, ſéeing euen our thoughts are poiſoned. If this doctrine ſéemeth to rough we muſt remember that it was the ſaieng of our merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full &amp; louing God, euen of that God that loueth man déerelie, and ſent his onelie ſonne to ſuffer a moſt horrible and a ſhamefull death for vs miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men: and that alſo, euen when we were his enimies, I ſaie it was
<pb facs="tcp:2469:90"/> the ſaieng of this God, Whenſoeuer thou eateſt of the forbidden trée, thou ſhalt die y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deth. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trariwiſe, it was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaieng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enuious ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which was a manſlaier fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father &amp; prince of tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, which gapeth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually for bloud, &amp; goeth about like a roaring Lion, ſéeking whom he may deſtroy, I ſay it was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaieng of this our profeſt &amp; ſworne enimie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide no truce w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs, you ſhal not die at al. But if we mark to what a ſower death, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſwéet words of this flatterer tended, we ſhall be forced to confeſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they wer more bitter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wormwood: &amp; that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wounds of him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> loueth are farre better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kiſſes of him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth. We muſt therfore reſiſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> diuel, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he wil flie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs: I grone for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> amendme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of theſe men, &amp; what ſhold I ſaie vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? I wil ſhew vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yet a little their owne eſtate, to the end they may repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t I wold deſire the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feare of God to examine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, by ſuch places of ſcripture as I will ſhew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. We read in. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. 4. verſe of the. 28. of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prouerbs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoſe
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:2469:90"/> that forſake the lawe praiſe the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: but thoſe that kéep y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law do fight againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. We read in. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. xv. pſalme that he ſhall dwell in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tabernacle of God, in whoſe eies a wicked man is deſpiſed, &amp; which doth honour thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> feare God. He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> approueth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked, &amp; condemneth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> innocent, both of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are an abhominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord. Now let them marke themſelues, whether they be more readie to blaze abrode y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> infirmitie of thoſe, which are not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med openlie to profeſſe Chriſt, &amp; his religion: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are to vtter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lewd behauior of thoſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for any thing they can perceiue, lie ſtill in their accurſed eſtate: when an vnſatiable man reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, or a wicked vaine man, is but a little touched, then we muſt iudge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beſt: we do not know their hearts, we cannot indéed ſée directlie into their hearts, no more then I can ſée y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hart of him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted actual whoor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, or actuall murder: but by their couetous, vaine &amp; proud behauiour, &amp; words, we knowe they haue proude hearts, vaine, and couetous heartes,
<pb facs="tcp:2469:91"/> for out of the abundance of the heart the mouth ſpeaketh. How can I ſet my ſelfe againſt a wicked man. How can I diſpiſe him, if I cannot tell (without iudgeing) who is wicked? In the Chapter of the Prouerbs that I laſt alledged, it is ſaid, that he that hideth his ſinne, ſhall not proſper: but he that confeſſeth &amp; forſaketh them, ſhall haue mercie. Happie is he that alwaies ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth in awe: but he which hardneth his hart ſhall fall into euill. Reioice O you<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g man (ſaith the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher) in thy youth, walke in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waies of thine heart, and in the ſight of thine eies: but knowe, that for all theſe things God will bring thée to iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. We vſe to alledge the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall inclination to naughtineſſe that is in man, to the end more libertie of ſinning might be graunted him: we are no Angels, and ſo foorth: but the conſideration thereof ought to make vs more warie, and more afraide of ſin, &amp; of the occaſions of ſinne, as the 12. verſe of the. 6. Chapter to the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians</hi> teacheth vs. We thinke if
<pb facs="tcp:2469:91"/> wée maie haue ſo much time, a lit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> before we die, as to ſaie, Lord hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mercie vpon me, they ſhall doe well enough. But the Scripture ſaith, not euerie one that ſaith, Lord Lord, ſhall enter into the kingdome of heauen: They ſhall call vppon me (ſaith the Lord) and I wil not heare them. The<note place="margin">Pre. 1.</note> reaſon is, becauſe they aſke not in faith: for euerie man beléeueth not, faith is no light opinion. We thinke we maie repent timelie enough, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are olde, or whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are gréeuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſicke: but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Scripture ſaith, driue not off from daie to daie, to turne to the Lord: for ſodeinlie ſhall his wrath come. Chriſt ſaith to all ſuch, that their maiſter wil come at ſuch a time as they leaſt looke for him. <hi>Hieremie</hi> in his lamentations giueth vs better counſell then ſo: It is good (ſaith he) for a man to beare the yoke in his youth, contrarie to that diuelliſh ſaieng of ſome, A young Saint, and an olde di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell. For teach a childe in the trade of his youth, &amp; when he is olde he wll not depart from it. I remember mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb facs="tcp:2469:92"/> 
                     <hi>Aſcham</hi> ſaith, that there was a Iudge in England, that had a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of wilde Gentlemen brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him for their miſbehauiour: they deſire the Iudge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he would conſider their caſe by his owne, becauſe he himſelfe had ben ſomtimes wilde as they were. But the Iudge willeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in anie caſe not to preſume of his recouerie, for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I was young, ther was twelue of vs (ſaith he) that rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted then, as you do now, but onelie two of vs came to good, the reſt were hanged. I doe not ſpeake this, to the end that anie gameſter, that hath a miſliking of his preſent eſtate, ſhould diſpaire of himſelfe: for though the waie be ſtraight y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> leadeth vnto life, yet the Lord can make vs crucifie our affections, &amp; denie our ſelues: his yoke ſhall then be eaſie, and his bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den light, the keping of the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, (as <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith) ſhall not then<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 5. 3.</note> be gréeuous: for all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is borne of god, ouercommeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> world. <hi>Salomon,</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of theſe waies of wiſdome, ſaith, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> her waies are waies of pleaſure, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:2469:92"/> all her paths proſperitie. Throw thy ſelfe downe therefore before the foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtole of Ieſus Chriſt, whatſoeuer t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ou art, with ſighing &amp; ſobbing: then hough gamſters haue ben thine one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ioie, &amp; darling, yet he can make thée forget all, euen by that mightie power whereby he is able to ſubdue all things vnto himſelf, ſhal he bring this thing to paſſe. Though by this meanes thou doeſt well perceiue, that thou ſhalt forgoe the louing counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance of a great manie: yet the Lord will be vnto thée in ſtéed of all. For he will comfort thée on this manner. If you were of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> world wold loue you, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world loueth hir owne, ſuch loue as it is wont to vſe, you ſhould haue part of it: but now you are not of the world, therefore the world hates you. If the world hateth you, it hated me before you: be of good chéere, I haue ouercome the world, feare not little flock, for it is your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers will to giue you a kingdome. Thoſe that ſow in teares, ſhall reape in ioie.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:2469:93"/>
            <p>¶ <hi>Imprinted at London</hi> by Thomas Eaſt, for Iohn Hariſon the younger, dwelling in Pater noſter Roe, at the ſigne of the Anker, and are there to be ſolde.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2469:93"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
